<!-- WSDG Chapter Tools -->
<!-- $Id$ -->

<chapter id="ChapterTools">
  <title>Tools</title>
  <section id="ChToolsIntro">
    <title>Introduction</title>
	<para>
	This chapter will provide you with information how to install 
	the various tools needed for Wireshark development.
	</para>
	<para>
	None of the tools mentioned in this chapter is needed to run Wireshark,
	they are only needed to build it.
	</para>
	<para>
	All these tools have
	their roots on UNIX like platforms, but Win32 ports are also
	available. Therefore the tools are available in different "flavours":
	<itemizedlist>
  	<listitem>
	<para>
	UNIX (or Win32 Cygwin): as described above, the tools should be commonly 
	available on the supported UNIX platforms, and for Win32 platforms by the 
	Cygwin UNIX emulation
	</para>
  	</listitem>
  	<listitem>
	<para>
	Win32 native: some tools are available as native Win32 tools, no 
	emulation is required (however, as the installation can be complicated, 
	using the Cygwin tools is recommended)
	</para>
  	</listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	</para>
	<para>
	General instructions to install the tools are given in:
	<xref linkend="ChToolsInstallUNIX"/> and 
	<xref linkend="ChToolsInstallWin32"/>.
	</para>
	<para>
	The following sections give a very brief description of 
	what the particular tool is doing, how it is used in the Wireshark project 
	and how it can be installed and tested.
	</para>
	<para>
	Don't expect a lot of documentation regarding these tools in this
	document. If you need further documentation of a specific tool, you
	should find lot's of useful information on the web, as these tools are
	commonly used. As all of the tools are command line tools, you can try 
	to get help with <userinput>toolname --help</userinput> or read
	the manpage <userinput>man toolname</userinput>.
	</para>
	<para>
	You will find explanations of the tool usage for some of the specific 
	development tasks in <xref linkend="ChapterSources"/>.
	</para>
  </section>
  
  <section id="ChToolsInstallUNIX">
	<title>UNIX: Installation</title>	
	<para>
	All the tools required are usually installed on a UNIX developer machine.
	</para>
	<para>
	If a tool is not already installed on your system, you will typically use 
	the installation package from your distribution (by your favourite package 
	manager: apt, yum, synaptics, ...).
	</para>
	<para>
	If an install package is not available, or you have a reason not to use 
	it (maybe because it's simply too old), you can install that tool 
	from source code. The following sections will provide you with the webpage
	addresses where you can get these sources. 
	</para>
  </section>

  <section id="ChToolsInstallWin32">
  <title>Win32: Installation</title>
	<para>
	The tool installation on Win32 can be quite confusing as there are several 
	ways to do so. 
	The following will give you a step-by-step guide to install the 
	development tools in the recommended way.
	<warning><title>Warning!</title>
	<para>
	<command>Unless you know exactly what you are doing, you should strictly 
	follow the recommendations!</command>
	</para>
	</warning>
	</para>

	<section id="ChToolsInstallWin32Recommended">
	<title>Recommendations (Cygwin vs. Win32 native)</title>
	<para>
	Cygwin provides a lot of UNIX based tools on the Win32 platform. It uses
	a UNIX emulation layer which might be a bit slower compared to the native 
	Win32 tools, but at an acceptable level.
	The installation and update is pretty easy and done through a single 
	(web based) setup.exe.
	</para>
	<para>
	The native Win32 tools will typically be a bit faster, but more 
	complicated to install. 
	You will have to download the tools from different webpages, 
	and install them in different ways, tweaking the PATH and alike. 
	</para>
	<note><title>Note!</title>
	<para>
	As there's no Win32 native bash version available, at least a basic 
	installation of cygwin is required in any case.
	</para>
	</note>
	<para>
	For all these reasons, the following recommends to use Cygwin tools where 
	appropriate.
	</para>
	
	<para>
	<table frame='all'><title>The recommended tools</title>
	<tgroup cols='4' align='left' colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
	<colspec colname='c1'/>
	<colspec colname='c2'/>
	<colspec colname='c3'/>
	<colspec colname='c4'/>
	<thead>
	<row>
	  <entry>Tool</entry>
	  <entry><link linkend="ChToolsInstallCygwin">Cygwin</link> (Category/Package)</entry>
	  <entry>Win32 native</entry>
	  <entry>Remark</entry>
	</row>
	</thead>
	<tbody>
	<row>
	  <entry><xref linkend="ChToolsCompiler"/></entry>
	  <entry>-</entry>
	  <entry>cl.exe (MSVC V6)</entry>
	</row>
	<row>
	  <entry><xref linkend="ChToolsDebugger"/></entry>
	  <entry>-</entry>
	  <entry>integrated debugger (MSVC V6)</entry>
	</row>
	<row>
	  <entry><xref linkend="ChToolsMake"/></entry>
	  <entry>-</entry>
	  <entry>nmake.exe (MSVC V6)</entry>
	</row>
	<row>
	  <entry><xref linkend="ChToolsBash"/></entry>
	  <entry>Base/bash</entry>
	  <entry>-</entry>
	  <entry>No Win32 native version available!</entry>
	</row>
	<row>
	  <entry><xref linkend="ChToolsSed"/></entry>
	  <entry>Base/sed</entry>
	  <entry>-</entry>
	</row>
	<row>
	  <entry><xref linkend="ChToolsPython"/></entry>
	  <entry>-</entry>
	  <entry>Python</entry>
	  <entry>Cygwin Python don't work on some machines</entry>
	</row>
	<row>
	  <entry><xref linkend="ChToolsPerl"/></entry>
	  <entry>Interpreters/perl</entry>
	  <entry>-</entry>
	</row>
	<row>
	  <entry><xref linkend="ChToolsYacc"/></entry>
	  <entry>Devel/bison</entry>
	  <entry>-</entry>
	</row>
	<row>
	  <entry><xref linkend="ChToolsLexx"/></entry>
	  <entry>Devel/flex</entry>
	  <entry>-</entry>
	</row>
	<row>
	  <entry><xref linkend="ChToolsWget"/></entry>
	  <entry>Web/wget</entry>
	  <entry>-</entry>
	</row>
	<row>
	  <entry><xref linkend="ChToolsUnzip"/></entry>
	  <entry>Archive/unzip</entry>
	  <entry>-</entry>
	</row>
	<row>
	  <entry><xref linkend="ChToolsSubversion"/></entry>
	  <entry>-</entry>
	  <entry>Subversion</entry>
	  <entry>Only needed if you access the Wireshark sources using 
	  the subversion repository (the recommended way).</entry>
	</row>
	<row>
	  <entry><xref linkend="ChToolsSubversionGUI"/></entry>
	  <entry>-</entry>
	  <entry>TortoiseSVN</entry>
	  <entry>Only needed if you access the Wireshark sources using 
	  the subversion repository (the recommended way).</entry>
	</row>
	<row>
	  <entry><xref linkend="ChToolsNSIS"/></entry>
	  <entry>-</entry>
	  <entry>NSIS</entry>
	  <entry>Only needed if you want to build your own 
	  wireshark-setup.exe.</entry>
	</row>
	</tbody>
	</tgroup>
	</table>
	Don't get confused by the (optional) marker at some of the items in the 
	"Tool" column. 
	Although these tools are not required to <command>build</command> 
	Wireshark they can make development life much easier and some are even 
	required by the following installation procedure.
	</para>
	</section>

	<section id="ChToolsInstallMSVC">
	<title>Install Microsoft Visual Studio Version 6</title>
	<para>
	Install MSVC the usual way. Don't forget to install vcvars32.bat or call 
	it manually before building Wireshark. vcvars32.bat will set some required 
	environment settings.
	</para>
	<warning><title>Warning!</title>
	<para>
	Using any other MSVC version is not recommended and will certainly not 
	work (at least without a lot of advanced tweaking). 
	For further details on this topic, see <xref linkend="ChToolsCompiler"/>.
	</para>
	</warning>
	</section>
	<section id="ChToolsInstallCygwin">
	<title>Install Cygwin</title>
	<para>
	Although Cygwin consists of several	seperate packages, the installation 
	and update is done through a single setup.exe, which acts similar to other 
	web based installers.
	All tools will be installed into one base folder, the default is 
	<filename>C:\cygwin</filename>.
	</para>
	<para>
	You will find this network based setup.exe at: <ulink 
	url="http://www.cygwin.com/"/>. Click on one of the "Install Cygwin now" 
	appearances to download the <filename>setup.exe</filename>.
	After the download completed, start this <filename>setup.exe</filename> 
	on your machine. 
	</para>
	<para>
	The setup will ask you for some settings, the defaults should usually 
	work well for a first start. 
	At the "Select Packages" page, you'll need to select some additional 
	packages, which are not installed by default. 
	Navigate to the required Category/Package row and click on the "Skip" 
	item in the "New" column so it shows a version number for:
	<itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>
	Archive/unzip
	</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>
	Devel/bison
	</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>
	Devel/flex
	</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>
	Interpreters/perl
	</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>
	Utils/patch
	</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>
	Web/wget
	</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	</para>	
	<para>
	After clicking the Next button several times, the setup will then 
	download and install the selected packages (this may take a while).
	</para>
	<para>
	Under: "Start -&gt; Programs -&gt; Cygwin -&gt; Cygwin Bash Shell" you
	should now be able to start a new Cygwin bash shell, which is similar to 
	the command line (command.exe/cmd.exe) in Win32, but much more powerful.
	</para>
	<section id="ChToolsInstallCygwinPackages">
	<title>Add/Update/Remove Cygwin Packages</title>	
	<para>
	If you want to add additional, update installed or remove packages later, 
	you have to start the setup.exe again. 
	At the "Select Packages" page, the entry in the "New" column will control 
	what is done (or not) with the package. If a new version of a package is 
	available, the new version number will be displayed, so it will be 
	automatically updated. 
	You can change the current setting by simply clicking at it, it will 
	change between:
	<itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	<para>
	a specific version number - this different package version will be 
	installed
	</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	<para>
	Skip - not installed, no changes
	</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	<para>
	Keep - already installed, no changes
	</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	<para>
	Uninstall - uninstall this package
	</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	<para>
	Reinstall - reinstall this package
	</para>
	</listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	</para>
	</section>
	</section>

	<section id="ChToolsInstallPython">
	<title>Install Python</title>	
	<para>
	Get the python installer from: 
	<ulink url="http://python.org/download/"/>
	and install python into the default location (currently: C:/Python24).
	</para>
	</section>
	
	<section id="ChToolsInstallAdditional">
	<title>Install Additional Tools</title>	
	<para>
	Depending on your actual task the following tools are recommended. 
	Please note that they are not required to build Wireshark but can be 
	quite helpful.
	</para>
	<section>
	<title>Subversion</title>
	<para>
	If you want to work with the Wireshark subversion source repositories 
	(which is highly recommended, see <xref linkend="ChSrcObtain"/>), 
	it's recommended to install Subversion. 
	This makes the first time setup easy and enables the Wireshark build 
	process to determine your current source code revision.
	You can download the setup from 
	<ulink url="http://subversion.tigris.org/"/> and simply install it.
	</para>
	</section>
	<section>
	<title>TortoiseSVN</title>
	<para>
	If you want to work with the Wireshark subversion source repositories 
	(which is highly recommended, see <xref linkend="ChSrcObtain"/>), 
	it's recommended to use TortoiseSVN for your everyday work. 
	You can download the setup from <ulink 
	url="http://tortoisesvn.tigris.org/"/> and simply install it.
	</para>
	</section>
	<section>
	<title>Nullsoft Scriptable Install System (NSIS)</title>
	<para>
	If you want to build your own wireshark-setup.exe, you'll need NSIS. 
	You can download the NSIS setup from 
	<ulink url="http://nsis.sourceforge.net"/> and simply install it.
	</para>
	<para>
	You may check the MAKENSIS setting in the file 
	<filename>config.nmake</filename> of the Wireshark sources.
	</para>
	</section>
	</section>

	<section id="ChToolsWin32Verify">
	<title>Verify installed tools</title>
	<para>
	After you've installed the Wireshark sources (see <xref 
	linkend="ChSrcObtain"/>), you can check the correct installation of 
	all tools by using the verify_tools target of the 
	<filename>Makefile.nmake</filename> from the source package.
	</para>
	<warning><title>Warning!</title>
	<para>
	You will need the Wireshark sources and some tools (nmake, bash) installed, 
	before this verification is able to work.
	</para>
	</warning>
	<para>
	Enter at the command line (cmd.exe, not Cygwin's bash!):
	</para>
	<para>
	<prompt>&gt;</prompt> 
	<userinput>nmake -f Makefile.nmake verify_tools</userinput>
	</para>
	<para>
	This will check for the various tools needed to build Wireshark:
	</para>
	<para>
	<programlisting>
<![CDATA[Checking for required applications:
        cl: /cygdrive/c/Program Files/Microsoft Visual Studio/VC98/bin/cl
        link: /cygdrive/c/Program Files/Microsoft Visual Studio/VC98/bin/link
        nmake: /cygdrive/c/Program Files/Microsoft Visual Studio/VC98/bin/nmake

        bash: /usr/bin/bash
        bison: /usr/bin/bison
        flex: /usr/bin/flex
        env: /usr/bin/env
        grep: /usr/bin/grep
        /usr/bin/find: /usr/bin/find
        perl: /usr/bin/perl
        env: /usr/bin/env
		C:/python24/python.exe: /cygdrive/c/python24/python.exe
        sed: /usr/bin/sed
        unzip: /usr/bin/unzip
        wget: /usr/bin/wget]]>
	</programlisting>
	</para>	
	<para>	
	If you have problems with all the first three ones, check if you called 
	...\Microsoft Visual Studio\VC98\Bin\vcvars32.bat before 
	(which will "fix" your PATH settings).
	</para>	
	<para>	
	Unfortunately, the link command is defined both from cygwin and from MSVC 
	with completely different purpose, you'll need the MSVC link. 
	If your link command looks something like: /usr/bin/link, the link command 
	of cygwin takes precedence over the MSVC one. To fix this, you can change 
	your PATH environment setting or simply renaming the link.exe in cygwin. 
	If you rename it, make sure to remember that a cygwin update may provide 
	a new version of it.
	</para>	
	</section>
	</section>

	<section id="ChToolsCompiler">
	<title>C compiler</title>
	
	<section id="ChToolsGCC">
	<title>UNIX or Win32 Cygwin: GCC (GNU compiler collection)</title>
	<note><title>Win32 Note!</title>
	<para>
	Although some effort is currently made to use gcc from the Cygwin
	environment, the mainline for several reasons is still using Microsoft 
	Visual Studio's C compiler.
	</para>
	</note>
	<para>
	The GCC C compiler is available for most of the UNIX-like platforms and 
	as the <application>Devel/gcc</application> package from the <link 
	linkend="ChToolsInstallCygwin">Cygwin setup</link>.
	</para>
	<para>
	If GCC isn't already installed and also not available as a package 
	for your platform, you can get it at: 
	<ulink url="http://gcc.gnu.org/"/>.
	</para>
	<para>
	After correct installation, typing inside the bash:
	</para>
	<para>
	<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>gcc --version</userinput>
	</para>
	<para>
	should result in something like:
	<programlisting>
<![CDATA[gcc (GCC) 3.4.4 (cygwin special) (gdc 0.12, using dmd 0.125)
Copyright (C) 2004 Free Software Foundation, Inc.
This is free software; see the source for copying conditions.  There is NO
warranty; not even for MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.]]>
	</programlisting>
	However, the version string may vary.
	</para>
	</section>
	 
	<section id="ChToolsMSVC6">
	<title>Win32 native: Microsoft Visual Studio version 6 C compiler</title>
	<para>
	<note><title>Note!</title>
	<para>
	The Microsoft Visual Studio is not free software.
	This is a tool you have to buy before you use it!
	</para>
	</note>
	</para>
	<para>
	The mainline for generating Wireshark on the windows platform, is using
	the compiler cl.exe from the Microsoft Visual Studio version 6 (and it's 
	nmake, as described below).
	</para>
	<para>
	After correct installation, typing inside the command line (cmd.exe):
	</para>
	<para>
	<prompt>&gt;</prompt> <userinput>cl</userinput>
	</para>
	<para>
	should result in something like:
	<programlisting>
<![CDATA[Microsoft (R) 32-bit C/C++ Optimizing Compiler Version 12.00.8804 for 80x86
Copyright (C) Microsoft Corp 1984-1998. All rights reserved.

usage: cl [ option... ] filename... [ /link linkoption... ]]]>
	</programlisting>
	However, the version string may vary.
	</para>
	</section>

	<section id="ChToolsMSVC7">
	<title>Win32 native: Microsoft Visual Studio .NET (and alike) C compilers
	</title>
	<para>
	<warning><title>Warning!</title>
	<para>
	The recent "Microsoft Visual Studio .NET" C compiler(s) currently cannot 
	be used to compile Wireshark!!!
	</para>
	</warning>
	</para>
	<para>
	The following is a problem summary for:
	<itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>
	Microsoft Visual Studio .NET
	</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>
	Microsoft Visual C++ .NET
	</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>
	Microsoft Visual C++ Toolkit 2003, freely available at: <ulink url="http://msdn.microsoft.com/visualc/vctoolkit2003/"/>
	</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	All containing version 7 or later of Microsoft's C compiler.
	</para>
	<para>
	It is reported that this compiler requires to ship a MSVCRT70.dll together 
	with the compiled exe, which contains the C runtime library. This 
	conflicts, as all required libraries currently compiled with (and uses) 
	MSVCRT.dll (the older version 6 one). 
	</para>
	<para>
	Example why this hurts: A dependant library might try to open a file using 
	functions in MSVCRT.dll which creates an internal file handle and keeps 
	information about that file. When Wireshark tries to read data from that 
	file, it uses the functions from MSVCRT70.dll, which doesn't know anything 
	about that previously opened file and returns an error code.
	</para>
	<para>
	There where also attempts to bring the compiler to use only the old 
	MSVCRT.dll but they seemed to fail :-(
	</para>
	<para>
	It's also still unsure, if shipping the MSVCRT70.dll together with Wireshark
	is compatible with the GPL license at all.	
	</para>
	<note><title>Note!</title>
	<para>
	This isn't an Wireshark specific problem. Any software project trying to use
	the version 7 C compiler will have the problems described above!
	</para>
	</note>
	<para>
	XXX - what about the legal issue, as the MSVCRT70.dll had to be shipped 
	with Wireshark.
	</para>
	</section>

	</section>

	<section id="ChToolsDebugger">
	<title>Debugger</title>
	<para>
	Well, using a good debugger can save you a lot of development time. However
	some people still think it's use is optional.
	</para>
	<para>
	The debugger you use must match the C compiler Wireshark was compiled with, 
	otherwise the debugger will simply fail or you will only see a lot of 
	garbage.
	</para>

	<section id="ChToolsGDB">
	<title>UNIX or Win32 Cygwin: GDB (GNU project debugger)</title>
	<para>
	GDB is the debugger for the GCC compiler. It is available for many (if 
	not all) UNIX-like platforms and as the <application>Devel/gdb</application> 
	package from the <link 
	linkend="ChToolsInstallCygwin">Cygwin setup</link>	
	</para>
	<para>
	If you don't like debugging using the command line, there are some GUI 
	frontends for it available, most notably GNU DDD.
	</para>
	<para>
	If gdb isn't already installed and also not available as a package for 
	your platform, you can get it at: 
	<ulink url="http://www.gnu.org/software/gdb/gdb.html"/>.
	</para>
	<para>
	After correct installation:
	</para>
	<para>
	<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>gdb --version</userinput>
	</para>
	<para>
	should result in something like:
	<programlisting>
<![CDATA[GNU gdb 6.5.50.20060706-cvs (cygwin-special)
Copyright 2003 Free Software Foundation, Inc.
GDB is free software, covered by the GNU General Public License, and you are
welcome to change it and/or distribute copies of it under certain conditions.
Type "show copying" to see the conditions.
There is absolutely no warranty for GDB.  Type "show warranty" for details.
This GDB was configured as "i686-pc-cygwin".]]>
	</programlisting>
	However, the version string may vary.
	</para>
	</section>

	<section id="ChToolsDDD">
	<title>UNIX: DDD (GNU Data Display Debugger)</title>
	<para>
	The GNU Data Display Debugger is a good GUI frontend for GDB (and a lot of 
	other command line debuggers), so you have to install GDB first. It is 
	available for many UNIX-like platforms and as the 
	<application>ddd</application> package from the <link 
	linkend="ChToolsInstallCygwin">Cygwin setup</link>.
	</para>
	<para>
	If GNU DDD isn't already installed and also not available as a package for 
	your platform, you can get it at: 
	<ulink url="http://www.gnu.org/software/ddd/"/>.
	</para>
	</section>

	<section id="ChToolsMSVCDebugger">
	<title>Win32 native: Microsoft Visual Studio debugger</title>
	<para>
	You can use the integrated debugger of Visual Studio. 
	</para>
	<para>
	However, setting up 
	the environment is a bit tricky, as the Win32 build process is using 
	makefiles instead of the .dsp/.dsw files usually used. 
	XXX - add instructions how to do it.
	</para>
	</section>
	
	<section id="ChToolsMSDebuggingTools">
	<title>Win32 native: Microsoft Debugging Tools for Windows</title>
	<para>
	You could also use the Microsoft debugging tools, which is a GUI debugger. 
	As it's not that comfortable compared to debugging in Visual Studio, it 
	can be helpful if you have to debug on a different machine.
	</para>
	<para>	
	You can get it free of charge at: <ulink 
	url="http://www.microsoft.com/whdc/devtools/debugging/default.mspx"/> (as
	links to microsoft pages changes from time to time, search for 
	"Debugging Tools" at their page if this link should be outdated).
	</para>
	</section>

	</section>

	<section id="ChToolsMake">
	<title>make</title>

	<section id="ChToolsGNUmake">
	<title>UNIX or Win32 Cygwin: GNU Make</title>
	<note><title>Win32 Note!</title>
	<para>
	Although some effort is made to use make from the Cygwin environment,
	the mainline is still using Microsoft Visual Studio's nmake.
	</para>
	</note>
	<para>
	GNU Make is available for most of the UNIX-like platforms and 
	also as the <application>Devel/make</application> package from the <link 
	linkend="ChToolsInstallCygwin">Cygwin setup</link>.
	</para>
	<para>
	If GNU Make isn't already installed and also not available as a package 
	for your platform, you can get it at: 
	<ulink url="http://www.gnu.org/software/make/"/>.
	</para>
	<para>
	After correct installation:
	</para>
	<para>
	<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>make --version</userinput>
	</para>
	<para>
	should result in something like:
	<programlisting>
<![CDATA[GNU Make 3.81
Copyright (C) 2006  Free Software Foundation, Inc.
This is free software; see the source for copying conditions.
There is NO warranty; not even for MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A
PARTICULAR PURPOSE.]]>
	</programlisting>
	However, the version string may vary.
	</para>
	</section>

	<section id="ChToolsNmake">
	<title>Win32 native: nmake from MSVC</title>
	<para>
	nmake is part of the Microsoft Visual Studio suite, see comment above.
	</para>
	<para>
	Instead of using the the workspace (.dsw) and projects (.dsp) files,
	the traditional nmake makefiles are used. This has one main reason: it
	makes it much easier to maintain changes simultaneous with the GCC
	toolchain makefile.am files as both file formats are similar. However, as
	no Visual Studio workspace/project files are available, this makes it
	hard to use the Visual Studio IDE e.g. for using the integrated
	debugging feature.
	</para>
	<para>
	After correct installation, typing inside the command line (cmd.exe):
	</para>
	<para>
	<prompt>&gt;</prompt> <userinput>nmake</userinput>
	</para>
	<para>
	should result in something like:
	<programlisting>
<![CDATA[Microsoft (R) Program Maintenance Utility   Version 6.00.9782.0
Copyright (C) Microsoft Corp 1988-1998. All rights reserved.

NMAKE : fatal error U1064: MAKEFILE not found and no target specified
Stop.]]>
	</programlisting>
	However, the version string may vary.
	</para>
	</section>

	<section id="ChToolsNmake15">
	<title>Win32 native: nmake from microsoft.com</title>
	<warning><title>Warning!</title>
	<para>
	It is recommended to use the Microsoft Visual Studio version 6 to compile
	Wireshark for Win32, see <xref linkend="ChToolsCompiler"/>. Don't follow the
	instructions in this section, until you now what you are doing.
	</para>
	</warning>
	<para>
	NMAKE 1.5 can be downloaded from Microsoft.com if you search for 
	"KB132084". Unpack the archive by running it, and drop the 3 extracted 
	files in the MSVC++ Toolkit "bin" directory.
	</para>
	<para>
	You will also need <filename>win32.mak</filename>, which you can get from 
	the MS Win Platform SDK by browsing to <ulink 
	url="http://www.microsoft.com/msdownload/platformsdk/sdkupdate/"/>
	where you select the "Core SDK" and only tick the "Build Environment"
	(31MB) option. After a while, this SDK will be installed.
	</para>
	<para>
	From the start menu, choose "Programs"
	-> "Microsoft Platform SDK February 2003"
	-> "Open build environment window"
	-> (choose your OS Win2K/WinXP/Win2003)
	</para>
	</section>

	</section>

	<section id="ChToolsBash">
	<title>bash</title>
	<para>
	The bash shell is needed to run several shell scripts.
	</para>
	
	<section id="ChToolsGNUBash">
	<title>UNIX or Win32 Cygwin: GNU bash</title>
	<para>
	The bash is available for most of the UNIX-like platforms and as the 
	<application>bash</application> package from the <link 
	linkend="ChToolsInstallCygwin">Cygwin setup</link>.
	</para>
	<para>
	If the bash isn't already installed and also not available as a package 
	for your platform, you can get it at: 
	<ulink url="http://www.gnu.org/software/bash/bash.html"/>.
	</para>
	<para>
	After correct installation, typing inside any shell:
	</para>
	<para>
	<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>bash --version</userinput>
	</para>
	<para>
	should result in something like:
	<programlisting>
<![CDATA[GNU bash, version 3.1.17(6)-release (i686-pc-cygwin)
Copyright (C) 2005 Free Software Foundation, Inc.]]>
	</programlisting>
	However, the version string may vary.
	</para>
	</section>
	
	<section id="ChToolsWin32Bash">
	<title>Win32 native: -</title>
	<para>
	The authors don't know of any working Win32 native bash implementation.
	</para>
	</section>

	</section>


	<section id="ChToolsPython">
	<title>python</title>
	<para>
	Python is an interpreter based programming language. The homepage of
	the python project is: <ulink url="http://python.org/"/>.
	Python is used to generate some source files. 
	Python version 2.2 and above should be working fine.
	</para>

	<section id="ChToolsUnixPython">
	<title>UNIX or Win32 Cygwin: python</title>
	<para>
	Python is available for most of the UNIX-like platforms and as the 
	<application>python</application> package from the <link 
	linkend="ChToolsInstallCygwin">Cygwin setup</link>
	</para>
	<para>
	If Python isn't already installed and also not available as a package 
	for your platform, you can get it at: 
	<ulink url="http://www.python.org/"/>.
	</para>
	<para>
	After correct installation, typing inside the bash:
	</para>
	<para>
	<userinput>$ python -V</userinput>
	</para>
	<para>
	should result in something like:
	</para>
	<para>
	<computeroutput>Python 2.4.3</computeroutput>
	</para>
	<para>
	However, the version string may vary.
	</para>
	</section>

	<section id="ChToolsWin32Python">
	<title>Win32 native: python</title>
	<para>
	Have a look at <ulink url="http://python.org/download/"/>
	to download the latest stable release. You can download a setup there,
	which will install the python system typically into
	<filename>C:\Python24</filename> or similiar.
	</para>
	<para>
	After correct installation, typing inside the command line (cmd.exe) - 
	this must be entered in the Python directory, the installer won't set 
	the PATH:
	</para>
	<para>
	<prompt>C:\Python24&gt;</prompt> <userinput>python -V</userinput>
	</para>
	<para>
	should result in something like:
	<programlisting>
<![CDATA[Python 2.4.4]]>
	</programlisting>
	However, the version string may vary. 
	</para>
	</section>

	</section>


	<section id="ChToolsPerl">
	<title>perl</title>
	<para>
	Perl is an interpreter based programming language. The homepage of the
	perl project is: <ulink url="http://www.perl.com"/>.
	Perl is used to convert various text files into usable source code. 
	Perl version 5.6 and above should be working fine.
	</para>

	<section id="ChToolsUnixPerl">
	<title>UNIX or Win32 Cygwin: perl</title>
	<para>
	Perl is available for most of the UNIX-like platforms and as the 
	<application>perl</application> package from the <link 
	linkend="ChToolsInstallCygwin">Cygwin setup</link>.
	</para>
	<para>
	If perl isn't already installed and also not available as a package 
	for your platform, you can get it at: 
	<ulink url="http://www.perl.com/"/>.
	</para>
	<para>
	After correct installation, typing inside the bash:
	</para>
	<para>
	<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>perl --version</userinput>
	</para>
	<para>
	should result in something like:
	<programlisting>
<![CDATA[This is perl, v5.8.7 built for cygwin-thread-multi-64int
(with 1 registered patch, see perl -V for more detail)

Copyright 1987-2005, Larry Wall

Perl may be copied only under the terms of either the Artistic License or the
GNU General Public License, which may be found in the Perl 5 source kit.

Complete documentation for Perl, including FAQ lists, should be found on
this system using `man perl' or `perldoc perl'.  If you have access to the
Internet, point your browser at http://www.perl.com/, the Perl Home Page.]]>
	</programlisting>
	However, the version string may vary.
	</para>

	</section>

	<section id="ChToolsWin32Perl">
	<title>Win32 native: perl</title>
	<para>
	A native Win32 perl package can be obtained from 
	<ulink url="http://www.ActiveState.com"/>. The
	installation should be straightforward.
	</para>
	<para>
	After correct installation, typing inside the command line (cmd.exe):
	</para>
	<para>
	<prompt>&gt;</prompt> <userinput>perl -v</userinput>
	</para>
	<para>
	should result in something like:
	<programlisting>
<![CDATA[This is perl, v5.8.0 built for MSWin32-x86-multi-thread
(with 1 registered patch, see perl -V for more detail)

Copyright 1987-2002, Larry Wall

Binary build 805 provided by ActiveState Corp. http://www.ActiveState.com
Built 18:08:02 Feb  4 2003

...]]>
	</programlisting>
	However, the version string may vary.
	</para>
	</section>

	</section>

	<section id="ChToolsSed">
	<title>sed</title>
	<para>
	Sed it the streaming editor. It makes it easy for example to replace
	specially marked texts inside a source code file. The Wireshark build
	process uses this to stamp version strings into various places.
	</para>

	<section id="ChToolsUnixSed">
	<title>UNIX or Win32 Cygwin: sed</title>
	<para>
	Sed is available for most of the UNIX-like platforms and as the 
	<application>sed</application> package from the <link 
	linkend="ChToolsInstallCygwin">Cygwin setup</link>.
	</para>
	<para>
	If sed isn't already installed and also not available as a package 
	for your platform, you can get it at: 
	<ulink url="http://directory.fsf.org/GNU/sed.html"/> 
	</para>
	<para>
	After correct installation, typing inside the bash:
	</para>
	<para>
	<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>sed --version</userinput>
	</para>
	<para>
	should result in something like:
	<programlisting>
<![CDATA[GNU sed version 4.1.5
Copyright (C) 2003 Free Software Foundation, Inc.
This is free software; see the source for copying conditions.  There is NO
warranty; not even for MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE,
to the extent permitted by law.]]>
	</programlisting>
	However, the version string may vary.
	</para>
	</section>

	<section id="ChToolsWin32Sed">
	<title>Win32 native: sed</title>
	<para>
	A native Win32 sed package can be obtained from 
	<ulink url="http://gnuwin32.sourceforge.net/"/>. The
	installation should be straightforward.
	</para>
	</section>

	</section>

	<section id="ChToolsYacc">
	<title>yacc (bison)</title>
	<para>
	Bison is a free implementation of yacc.
	</para>

	<section id="ChToolsUnixYacc">
	<title>UNIX or Win32 Cygwin: bison</title>
	<para>
	Bison is available for most of the UNIX-like platforms and as the 
	<application>bison</application> package from the <link 
	linkend="ChToolsInstallCygwin">Cygwin setup</link>.
	</para>
	<para>
	If GNU Bison isn't already installed and also not available as a package 
	for your platform, you can get it at: 
	<ulink url="http://www.gnu.org/software/bison/bison.html"/>.
	</para>
	<para>
	After correct installation, typing inside the bash:
	</para>
	<para>
	<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>bison --version</userinput>
	</para>
	<para>
	should result in something like:
	<programlisting>
<![CDATA[bison (GNU Bison) 2.3
Written by Robert Corbett and Richard Stallman.

Copyright (C) 2006 Free Software Foundation, Inc.
This is free software; see the source for copying conditions.  There is NO
warranty; not even for MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.]]>
	</programlisting>
	However, the version string may vary.
	</para>
	</section>

	<section id="ChToolsWin32Yacc">
	<title>Win32 native: bison</title>
	<para>
	A native Win32 yacc/bison package can be obtained from 
	<ulink url="http://gnuwin32.sourceforge.net/"/>. The
	installation should be straightforward.
	</para>
	</section>
	</section>


	<section id="ChToolsLexx">
	<title>lexx (flex)</title>
	<para>
	Flex is a free implementation of lexx.
	</para>
	
	<section id="ChToolsUnixLexx">
	<title>UNIX or Win32 Cygwin: flex</title>
	<para>
	Flex is available for most of the UNIX-like platforms and as the 
	<application>flex</application> package from the <link 
	linkend="ChToolsInstallCygwin">Cygwin setup</link>.
	</para>
	<para>
	If GNU flex isn't already installed and also not available as a package 
	for your platform, you can get it at: 
	<ulink url="http://www.gnu.org/software/flex/"/>.
	</para>
	<para>
	After correct installation, typing inside the bash:
	</para>
	<para>
	<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>flex --version</userinput>
	</para>
	<para>
	should result in something like:
	<programlisting>
<![CDATA[flex version 2.5.4]]>
	</programlisting>
	However, the version string may vary.
	</para>
	</section>

	<section id="ChToolsWin32Lexx">
	<title>Win32 native: flex</title>
	<para>
	A native Win32 lexx/flex package can be obtained from 
	<ulink url="http://gnuwin32.sourceforge.net/"/>. The
	installation should be straightforward.
	</para>
	</section>
	</section>


	<section id="ChToolsSubversion">
	<title>Subversion (SVN) client (optional)</title>
	<para>
	The Wireshark project uses it's own subversion (or short SVN) server to keep 
	track of all the changes done to the source code. Details about the usage
	of subversion in the Wireshark project can be found in <xref 
	linkend="ChSrcSVNServer"/>.
	</para>
	<para>	
	If you want to work with the source code and planning to commit your
	changes back to the Wireshark community, it is recommended to use a SVN 
	client to get the latest source files. For detailed information about the 
	different ways to obtain the Wireshark sources, see 
	<xref linkend="ChSrcObtain"/>.
	</para>
	<para>
	You will find more instructions in <xref linkend="ChSrcAnon"/> how to 
	use the subversion client.
	</para>

	<section id="ChToolsUnixSVN">
	<title>UNIX or Win32 Cygwin: svn (subversion)</title>
	<para>
	SVN is available for most of the UNIX-like platforms and as the 
	<application>subversion</application> package from the <link 
	linkend="ChToolsInstallCygwin">Cygwin setup</link>
	</para>
	<para>
	If Subversion isn't already installed and also not available as a package 
	for your platform, you can get it at: 
	<ulink url="http://subversion.tigris.org/"/> (together with the server 
	software).
	</para>
	<para>
	After correct installation, typing inside the bash:
	</para>
	<para>
	<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>svn --version</userinput>
	</para>
	<para>
	should result in something like:
	<programlisting>
<![CDATA[svn, version 1.0.5 (r9954)
   compiled Jun 20 2004, 23:28:30

Copyright (C) 2000-2004 CollabNet.
Subversion is open source software, see http://subversion.tigris.org/
This product includes software developed by CollabNet (http://www.Collab.Net/).

...]]>
	</programlisting>
	However, the version string may vary.
	</para>
	</section>

	<section id="ChToolsWin32SVN">
	<title>Win32 native: svn</title>
	<para>
	The subversion command line tools for Win32 can be found at: 
	<ulink url="http://subversion.tigris.org/"/>. 
	This will come with both client and server software - only the client 
	software will be used.
	</para>
	<para>
	After correct installation, typing inside the command line (cmd.exe):
	</para>
	<para>
	<prompt>&gt;</prompt> <userinput>svn --version</userinput>
	</para>
	<para>
	should result in something like:
	<programlisting>
<![CDATA[svn, Version 1.4.0 (r21228)

Copyright (C) 2000-2006 CollabNet.
...]]>
	</programlisting>
	However, the version string may vary.
	</para>
	</section>
	</section>

	<section id="ChToolsSubversionGUI">
	<title>Subversion (SVN) GUI client (optional)</title>
	<para>
	Along with the traditional command-line client, several GUI clients are 
	available for a number of platforms, see
	<ulink url="http://subversion.tigris.org/project_links.html"/>.
	</para>
	<warning><title>Keep subversion program versions in sync!</title>
	<para>
	If you are working with both command line and GUI clients, keep
	the subversion program versions in sync, at least the major/minor versions 
	(e.g. 1.4).
	</para>
	</warning>

	<section id="ChToolsUnixSVNGUI">
	<title>UNIX or Win32 Cygwin: -</title>
	<para>
	XXX - could someone recommend a good UNIX GUI client for subversion?
	</para>
	<para>
	Cygwin don't provide any GUI client for subversion.
	</para>
	</section>

	<section id="ChToolsTortoiseSVN">
	<title>Win32 native: TortoiseSVN</title>
	<para>
	A good subversion client for Win32 can be found at: 
	<ulink url="http://tortoisesvn.tigris.org/"/>. It will nicely integrate 
	into the Windows Explorer window.
	</para>
	</section>

	</section>

	<section id="ChToolsDiff">
	<title>diff (optional)</title>
	<para>
	Diff is used to get a file of all differences between two source
	files/trees (sometimes called a patch). The diff tool isn't needed for 
	building Wireshark, but it's needed if you are going to commit your changes 
	back to the Wireshark community.
	</para>
	<note><title>Note!</title>
	<para>
	The recommended way to build patches is using the subversion client,
	see <xref linkend="ChToolsSubversion"/> for details.
	</para>
	</note>	
	<para>
	You will find more instructions in <xref linkend="ChSrcDiff"/> how to 
	use the diff tool.
	</para>

	<section id="ChToolsGNUDiff">
	<title>UNIX or Win32 Cygwin: GNU diff</title>
	<para>
	Diff is available for most of the UNIX-like platforms and as the 
	<application>diffutils</application> package from the <link 
	linkend="ChToolsInstallCygwin">Cygwin setup</link>.
	</para>
	<para>
	If GNU diff isn't already installed and also not available as a package 
	for your platform, you can get it at: 
	<ulink url="http://www.gnu.org/software/diffutils/diffutils.html"/>.
	</para>
	<para>
	After correct installation, typing inside the bash:
	</para>
	<para>
	<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>diff --version</userinput>
	</para>
	<para>
	should result in something like:
	<programlisting>
<![CDATA[diff (GNU diffutils) 2.8.7
Written by Paul Eggert, Mike Haertel, David Hayes,
Richard Stallman, and Len Tower.

Copyright (C) 2004 Free Software Foundation, Inc.
This is free software; see the source for copying conditions.  There is NO
warranty; not even for MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.]]>
	</programlisting>
	However, the version string may vary.
	</para>
	</section>

	<section id="ChToolsWin32Diff">
	<title>Win32 native: diff</title>
	<para>
	A native Win32 diff package can be obtained from 
	<ulink url="http://gnuwin32.sourceforge.net/"/>. The
	installation should be straightforward.
	</para>
	<para>
	The subversion client TortoiseSVN has a build in diff feature, see 
	<xref linkend="ChToolsTortoiseSVN"/>. If this can be used to create diff 
	files in the required format, so other persons can use them, is currently 
	unknown.
	</para>
	</section>

	</section>


	<section id="ChToolsPatch">
	<title>patch (optional)</title>
	<para>
	The patch utility is used to merge a diff file into your own source
	tree. This tool is only needed, if you want to apply a patch (diff file) 
	from someone else (probably from the developer mailing list) to try out 
	in your own private source tree.
	</para>
	<tip><title>Tip!</title>
	<para>
	Unless you are in the rare case needing to apply a patch to your private 
	source tree, you won't need the patch tool installed.
	</para>
	</tip>
	<para>
	You will find more instructions in <xref linkend="ChSrcPatchApply"/> how 
	to use the patch tool.
	</para>

	<section id="ChToolsUnixPatch">
	<title>UNIX or Win32 Cygwin: patch</title>
	<para>
	Patch is available for most of the UNIX-like platforms and as the 
	<application>patch</application> package from the <link 
	linkend="ChToolsInstallCygwin">Cygwin setup</link>.
	</para>
	<para>
	If GNU patch isn't already installed and also not available as a package 
	for your platform, you can get it at: 
	<ulink url="http://www.gnu.org/software/patch/patch.html"/>.
	</para>
	<para>
	After correct installation, typing inside the bash:
	</para>
	<para>
	<prompt>$</prompt> <userinput>patch --version</userinput>
	</para>
	<para>
	should result in something like:
	<programlisting>
<![CDATA[patch 2.5.8
Copyright (C) 1988 Larry Wall
Copyright (C) 2002 Free Software Foundation, Inc.

This program comes with NO WARRANTY, to the extent permitted by law.
You may redistribute copies of this program
under the terms of the GNU General Public License.
For more information about these matters, see the file named COPYING.

written by Larry Wall and Paul Eggert]]>
	</programlisting>
	However, the version string may vary.
	</para>
	</section>

	<section id="ChToolsWin32Patch">
	<title>Win32 native: patch</title>
	<para>
	A native Win32 patch package can be obtained from 
	<ulink url="http://gnuwin32.sourceforge.net/"/>. The
	installation should be straightforward.
	</para>
	<para>
	The subversion client TortoiseSVN has a build in patch feature, see 
	<xref linkend="ChToolsTortoiseSVN"/>. The last time tested (Version 1.1.0), 
	this feature failed to apply patches known to be ok.
	</para>
	</section>

	</section>


	<section id="ChToolsWget">
	<title>Win32: GNU wget (optional)</title>
	<para>
	GNU wget is used to download files from the internet using the command line.
	</para>
	<para>
	GNU wget is available for most of the UNIX-like platforms and as the 
	<application>wget</application> package from the <link 
	linkend="ChToolsInstallCygwin">Cygwin setup</link>.
	</para>
	<para>
	You will only need wget, if you want to use the Win32 automated library 
	download, see <xref linkend="ChLibsSetup"/> for details.
	</para>
	<para>
	If GNU wget isn't already installed and also not available as a package 
	for your platform (well, for Win32 it is available as a Cygwin package), 
	you can get it at: 
	<ulink url="http://www.gnu.org/software/wget/wget.html"/>.
	</para>
	<para>
	If wget is trying to download files but fails to do so, your internet 
	connection might use a HTTP proxy. Some Internet providers using such a 
	proxy and it is common for company networks today. In this case, you 
	must set the environment variable 
	http_proxy before using wget. For example, if you are behind proxy.com 
	which is listening on port 8080, you have to set it to something like:
	</para>
	<para>
	<programlisting>set HTTP_PROXY=http://proxy.com:8080/</programlisting>
	</para>
	<para>
	If you are unsure about the settings, you might ask your system 
	administrator.
	</para>
	</section>

	<section id="ChToolsUnzip">
	<title>Win32: GNU unzip (optional)</title>
	<para>
	GNU unzip is used to, well, unzip the zip files downloaded using the wget 
	tool.
	</para>
	<para>
	GNU wget is available for most of the UNIX-like platforms and as the 
	<application>unzip</application> package from the <link 
	linkend="ChToolsInstallCygwin">Cygwin setup</link>.
	</para>
	<para>
	You will only need unzip, if you want to use the Win32 automated library 
	download, see <xref linkend="ChLibsSetup"/> for details.
	</para>
	<para>
	If GNU unzip isn't already installed and also not available as a package 
	for your platform (well, for Win32 it is available as a Cygwin package), 
	you can get it at: 
	<ulink url="http://gnuwin32.sourceforge.net/packages/unzip.htm"/>.
	</para>
	</section>


	<section id="ChToolsNSIS">
	<title>Win32: NSIS (optional)</title>
	<para>
	The NSIS (Nullsoft Scriptable Install System) is used to generate a
	wireshark-setup-&lt;version&gt;.exe from all the files needed to be installed, including all
	required DLL's and such.
	</para>
	<para>
	To install it, simply download the latest released version (currently: 2.0
	final) from <ulink url="http://nsis.sourceforge.net"/>
	and start the downloaded installer. You will need NSIS version 2 final 
	or higher.
	</para>
	<para>
	You will find more instructions in <xref linkend="ChSrcNSIS"/> how to 
	use the NSIS tool.
	</para>
	</section>

</chapter>
<!-- End of WSDG Chapter Tools -->
