<!-- WSDG Chapter Works -->
<!-- $Id$ -->

<chapter id="ChapterWorks">
  <title>How Wireshark Works</title>
  
  <section id="ChWorksIntro">
	<title>Introduction</title>
	<para>
	This chapter will give you a short overview, how Wireshark is working.
	</para>
  </section>

  <section id="ChWorksOverview">
	<title>Overview</title>
	<para>
	The following will give you a simplified overview of Wiresharks function blocks:
	<figure id="ChWorksFigOverview">
	  <title>
	    <application>Wireshark</application> function blocks.
	  </title>
	  <graphic entityref="WiresharkFunctionBlocks" format="PNG"/>
	</figure>
	</para>
	<para>
	The function blocks in more detail:
	<variablelist>
	  <varlistentry><term><command>GTK 1/2</command></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		  Handling of all user input/output (all windows, dialogs and such). 
		  Source code can be found in the <filename>gtk</filename> directory.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry><term><command>Core</command></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		  Main "glue code" that holds the other blocks together, source 
		  code can be found in the root directory.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry><term><command>Epan</command></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		  Ethereal Packet ANalyzer (XXX - is this correct?) the packet 
		  analyzing engine, source code can be found in the 
		  <filename>epan</filename> directory.
	      </para>
	  <itemizedlist>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		  Protocol-Tree - Keep data of the capture file protocol information.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		  Dissectors - The various protocol dissectors in 
		  <filename>epan/dissectors</filename>.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		  Plugins - Some of the protocol dissectors are implemented as plugins, source 
		  code at <filename>plugins</filename>.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		  Display-Filters - the display filter engine at 
		  <filename>epan/dfilter</filename>.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry><term><command>Capture</command></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		  Capture engine.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry><term><command>Wiretap</command></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		  The wiretap library is used to read/write capture files in libpcap 
		  and a lot of other file formats, the source code is in the
		  <filename>wiretap</filename> directory.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry>
	  <term><command>Win-/libpcap (not part of the Wireshark package)</command></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		  The platform dependant packet capture library, including the capture 
		  filter engine. That's the reason why we still have different display 
		  and capture filter syntax, as two different filtering engines used.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	</variablelist>
	</para>
  </section>

	<section id="ChWorksCapturePackets">
	<title>Capturing packets</title>
	<para>
	Capturing will take packets from a network adapter, and save them to a file 
	on your harddisk. 
	</para>
	<para>
	To hide all the lowlevel machine dependant details from 
	Wireshark, the libpcap/WinPcap (see <xref linkend="ChLibsPcap"/>) library 
	is used. This library provides a general purpose interface to capture 
	packets from a lot of different network interface types (Ethernet, 
	Token Ring, ...). 
	</para>
	</section>

	<section id="ChWorksCaptureFiles">
	<title>Capture Files</title>
	<para>
	Wireshark can read and write capture files in it's natural file format, the 
	libpcap format, which is used by many other network capturing tools, 
	e.g. tcpdump. In addition to this, as one of it's strengths,
	Wireshark can read/write files in many different file formats of other 
	network capturing tools. The wiretap library, developed together with 
	Wireshark, provides a general purpose interface to read/write all the file 
	formats. If you need to add another capture file format, this is the place 
	to start.	
	</para>
	</section>

	<section id="ChWorksDissectPackets">
	<title>Dissect packets</title>
	<para>
	While Wireshark is loading packets from a file, each packet is dissected. 
	Wireshark tries to detect what kind of packet it is and getting as much 
	information from it as possible. In this run, only the information showed 
	in the packet list pane is needed though. 
	</para>
	<para>
	As the user selects a specific packet in the packet list pane, this packet
	will be dissected again. This time, Wireshark tries to 
	get every single piece of information and put it into 
	the packet details pane then.
	</para>
	</section>

</chapter>
<!-- End of WSDG Chapter Works -->
