<!-- $Id$ -->

<preface id="Preface">
  <title>Preface</title>
  <section id="PreForeword">
  <title>Foreword</title>
  <para>
    Wireshark is one of those programs that many network managers would love 
    to be able to use, but they are often prevented from getting what they 
    would like from Ethereal because of the lack of documentation.
  </para>
  <para>
    This document is part of an effort by the Ethereal team to improve the 
	usability of Ethereal.
  </para>
  <para>
    We hope that you find it useful, and look forward to your comments.
  </para>
  </section>

  <section id="PreAudience">
  <title>Who should read this document?</title>
  <para>
  The intended audience of this book is anyone using Ethereal.
  </para>
  <para>
  This book will explain all the basics and also some of the advanced features 
  that Ethereal provides. As Ethereal has become a very complex program since 
  the early days, not every feature of Ethereal might be explained in this 
  book. 
  </para>
  <para>
  This book is not intended to explain network sniffing in general and it will
  not provide details about specific network protocols. A lot of useful 
  information regarding these topics can be found at the Ethereal Wiki at
  <ulink url="&EtherealWikiPage;">&EtherealWikiPage;</ulink>
  </para>
  <para>
  By reading this book, you will learn how to install Ethereal, how to use the 
  basic elements of the graphical user interface (like the menu) and what's 
  behind some of the advanced features that are maybe not that obvious at first 
  sight. It will 
  hopefully guide you around some common problems that frequently appears for 
  new (and sometimes even advanced) users of Ethereal.
  </para>
  </section>

  <section id="PreAck">
  <title>Acknowledgements</title>
  <para>
    The authors would like to thank the whole Ethereal team for their 
	assistance. In particular, the authors would like to thank:
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Gerald Combs, for initiating the Ethereal project and funding to 
	  do this documentation.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Guy Harris, for many helpful hints and a great deal of patience 
	  in reviewing this document.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Gilbert Ramirez, for general encouragement and helpful hints along 
	  the way.
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </para>
  <para>
    The authors would also like to thank the following people for their 
	helpful feedback on this document:
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Pat Eyler, for his suggestions on improving the example on 
	  generating a backtrace.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Martin Regner, for his various suggestions and corrections.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Graeme Hewson, for a lot of grammatical corrections.
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </para>
  <para>
    The authors would like to acknowledge those man page and README authors 
	for the ethereal project from who sections of this document borrow heavily:
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Scott Renfro from whose <command>mergecap</command> man page 
	  <xref linkend="AppToolsmergecap"/> is derived.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Ashok Narayanan from whose <command>text2pcap</command> man page 
	  <xref linkend="AppToolstext2pcap"/> is derived.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Frank Singleton from whose <filename>README.idl2eth</filename> 
	  <xref linkend="AppToolsidl2eth"/> is derived. 
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </para>
  </section>

  <section id="PreAbout">
    <title>About this document</title>
    <para>
      This book was originally developed by 
      <ulink url="mailto:&AuthorEmail;">Richard Sharpe</ulink> with 
      funds provided from the Ethereal Fund. It was updated by 
	  <ulink url="mailto:&AuthorEmail2;">Ed Warnicke</ulink> and more recently 
	  redesigned and updated by <ulink url="mailto:&AuthorEmail3;">Ulf 
	  Lamping</ulink>.
    </para>
    <para>
      It is written in DocBook/XML.
    </para>
    <para>
	You will find some specially marked parts in this book:
    </para>
    <warning><title>This is a warning!</title>
	<para>
	You should pay attention to a warning, as otherwise data loss might occur.
	</para>
    </warning>
    <note><title>This is a note!</title>
	<para>
	A note will point you to common mistakes and things that might not be 
	obvious.
	</para>
    </note>
    <tip><title>This is a tip!</title>
	<para>
	Tips will be helpful for your everyday work using Ethereal.
	</para>
    </tip>
  </section>
  
  <section id="PreDownload">
    <title>Where to get the latest copy of this document?</title>
    <para>
      The latest copy of this documentation can always be found at: 
      <ulink url="&EtherealUsersGuidePage;"/>.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="PreFeedback">
    <title>Providing feedback about this document</title>
    <para>
      Should you have any feedback about this document, please send them 
      to the authors through <ulink url="mailto:&EtherealDevMailList;">&EtherealDevMailList;</ulink>.
    </para>
  </section>
</preface>
