<!-- EUG Chapter IO -->
<!-- $Id$ -->

<chapter id="ChapterIO">
  <title>File Input / Output and Printing</title>

  <section id="ChIOIntroductionSection"><title>Introduction</title>
    <para>
	This chapter will describe input and output of capture data.
	<itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Open/Import capture files in various capture file formats
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Save/Export capture files in various capture file formats
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	  Merge capture files together
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Print packets
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="ChIOOpenSection"><title>Open capture files</title>
    <para>
      Ethereal can read in previously saved capture files. 
	  To read them, simply select the menu or toolbar item: "File/
	  <inlinegraphic entityref="EtherealToolbarOpen" format="PNG"/>
	  <command>Open</command>".  
      Ethereal will then pop up the File 
      Open dialog box, which is discussed in more detail in 
      <xref linkend="ChIOOpen"/>. 
    </para>
	<note><title>Note!</title>
    <para>
	You can also use <command>drag-and-drop </command> to open a file, by 
	simply dropping the desired file from your file manager onto Ethereal's 
	main window. However, drag-and-drop is not available/won't work in all 
	desktop environments.
    </para>
    </note>
    <para>
	  If you didn't save the current capture file before, you will be asked 
	  to do so, to prevent data loss (this behaviour can be disabled in the 
	  preferences).
    </para>
    <para>
	  In addition to its native file format (libpcap format, also used by 
	  tcpdump/WinDump and other libpcap/WinPcap-based programs), Ethereal can 
	  read capture files from a large number of other packet capture programs 
	  as well. See <xref linkend="ChIOInputFormatsSection"/> for the list of 
	  capture formats Ethereal understands.
    </para>
	
    <section id="ChIOOpen"><title>The "Open Capture File" dialog box</title>
      <para>
	The "Open Capture File" dialog box allows you to search for a 
	capture file containing previously captured packets for display in 
	Ethereal.  <xref linkend="ChIOOpenFileDialog"/> shows an example 
	  of the Ethereal Open File Dialog box.
      </para>
	    <note>
	      <title>Note</title>
	      <para>
		  Ethereal uses the open dialog box from the version of the GTK+ 
		  toolkit that it's using. This dialog was completely redesigned in 
		  GTK version 2.4. Depending on the installed GTK version, 
		  your dialog box might look different. However, as the 
		  functionality remains almost the same, much of this description 
		  will work with your version of Ethereal.
	      </para>
	    </note>
      <figure id="ChIOOpenFileDialog">
	<title>The "Open Capture File" Dialog box</title>
	<graphic entityref="EtherealOpen" format="PNG"/>
      </figure>
      <para>
	With this dialog box, you can perform the following actions:
	<orderedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
		The "+ Add" button allows you to add a directory, selected in the 
		right-hand pane, to the favorites (bookmarks?) list. Those changes 
		are persistent.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
		The "- Remove" button allows you to remove a selected directory from 
		that list again (the items like: "Home", "Desktop", and "Filesystem" 
		cannot be removed).
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Select files and directories with the list boxes.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      View file preview information (like the filesize, the number of 
		  packets, ...), while browsing the filesystem.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Specify a display filter with the Filter button and filter 
	      field. This filter will be used when opening the new file.
		  Clicking on the Filter button causes Ethereal to pop up 
	      the Filters dialog box (which is discussed further in 
	      <xref linkend="ChWorkDisplayFilterSection"/>).
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Specify which name resolution is to be performed for all packets by 
		  clicking on one of the "Enable name resolution" check buttons. 
		  Details about name resolution can be found in 
		  <xref linkend="ChAdvNameResolutionSection"/>.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Click the Open button to accept your selected file and open it. 
		  If Ethereal doesn't recognize the capture format, it will grey out 
		  this button.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Click the Cancel button to go back to Ethereal and not load a capture 
	      file.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</orderedlist>
	You can also change the display filter and name resolution settings later while 
	viewing the packets. However, for very large capture files it can take a 
	significant amount of extra time changing these settings later, so it 
	might be a good idea to set at least the filter in advance here.
      </para>
    </section>

  <section id="ChIOInputFormatsSection">
    <title>Input File Formats</title>
    <para>
	The following file formats from other capture tools can be opened by 
	<application>Ethereal</application>:
	<itemizedlist>
	      <listitem><para>libpcap, tcpdump and various other tools using tcpdump's capture format</para></listitem>
	      <listitem><para>Sun snoop and atmsnoop</para></listitem>
	      <listitem><para>Shomiti/Finisar <emphasis>Surveyor</emphasis> captures</para></listitem>
	      <listitem><para>Novell <emphasis>LANalyzer</emphasis> captures</para></listitem>
	      <listitem><para>Microsoft Network Monitor captures</para></listitem>
	      <listitem><para>AIX's iptrace captures</para></listitem>
	      <listitem><para>Cinco Networks NetXray captures</para></listitem>		  
	      <listitem><para>Network Associates Windows-based Sniffer and Sniffer Pro captures</para></listitem>
		  <listitem><para>Network General/Network Associates DOS-based Sniffer (compressed or uncompressed) captures</para></listitem>
	      <listitem><para>AG Group/WildPackets EtherPeek/TokenPeek/AiroPeek/EtherHelp/PacketGrabber captures</para></listitem>
	      <listitem><para>RADCOM's WAN/LAN Analyzer captures</para></listitem>
		  <listitem><para>Network Instruments Observer version 9 captures</para></listitem>
		  <listitem><para>Lucent/Ascend router debug output</para></listitem>		  
	      <listitem><para>HP-UX's nettl</para></listitem>
	      <listitem><para>Toshiba's ISDN routers dump output</para></listitem>
	      <listitem><para>ISDN4BSD <emphasis>i4btrace</emphasis> utility</para></listitem>
		  <listitem><para>traces from the EyeSDN USB S0</para></listitem>
		  <listitem><para>IPLog format from the Cisco Secure Intrusion Detection System</para></listitem>
		  <listitem><para>pppd logs (pppdump format)</para></listitem>
		  <listitem><para>the output from VMS's TCPIPtrace/TCPtrace/UCX$TRACE utilities</para></listitem>
		  <listitem><para>the text output from the DBS Etherwatch VMS utility</para></listitem>
		  <listitem><para>Visual Networks' Visual UpTime traffic capture</para></listitem>
		  <listitem><para>the output from CoSine L2 debug</para></listitem>
		  <listitem><para>the output from Accellent's 5Views LAN agents</para></listitem>
		  <listitem><para>Endace Measurement Systems' ERF format captures</para></listitem>
		  <listitem><para>Linux Bluez Bluetooth stack hcidump -w traces</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
    </para>
    <note><title>Note!</title>
	<para>
	It may not be possible to read some formats dependent on the packet types 
	captured. Ethernet captures are usually supported for most file formats, 
	but other packet types (e.g. token ring packets) may not be possible to 
	read from all file formats.
	</para>
	</note>
	
  </section>

  </section>
  
  <section id="ChIOSaveSection"><title>Saving captured packets</title>
    <para>
      You can save captured packets simply by using the Save As... menu 
      item from the File menu under Ethereal. You can choose which 
      packets to save and which file format to be used.
    </para>
    <section id="ChIOSaveAs">
      <title>The "Save Capture File As" dialog box</title>
      <para>
	The "Save Capture File As" dialog box allows you to save 
	the current capture to a file. 
	<xref linkend="ChIOSaveCaptureFileAs"/> shows an example of this 
	  dialog box.
      </para>
	    <note>
	      <title>Note</title>
	      <para>
		  Ethereal uses the open dialog box from the version of the GTK+ 
		  toolkit that it's using. This dialog was completely redesigned in 
		  the GTK version 2.4. Depending on the installed GTK version, 
		  your dialog box might look different. However, as the 
		  functionality remains almost the same, much of this description 
		  will work with your version of Ethereal.
	      </para>
	    </note>
      <figure id="ChIOSaveCaptureFileAs">
	<title>The "Save Capture File As" dialog box</title>
	<graphic entityref="EtherealSaveAs" format="PNG"/>
      </figure>
      <para>
	With this dialog box, you can perform the following actions:
	<orderedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Type in the name of the file you wish to save the captured 
	      packets in, as a standard file name in your file system.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
		Select the directory to save the file into.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Select the range of the packets to be saved, see 
		  <xref linkend="ChIOPacketRangeSection"/>
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Specify the format of the saved capture file by clicking on 
	      the File type drop down box. You can choose from the 
	      types, described in <xref linkend="ChIOOutputFormatsSection"/>.
		</para>
	    <note>
	      <title>Note!</title>
	      <para>
		Some capture formats may not be available, depending on the 
		packet types captured.
	      </para>
	    </note>
	    <tip>
	      <title>Tip!</title>
	      <para>
		You can convert capture files from one format to another 
		by reading in a capture file and writing it out using a 
		different format.
	      </para>
	    </tip>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Use "Browse for other folders" to browse files and folders in your 
		  file system.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Click on the Save button to accept your selected file and save to 
		  it. If Ethereal has a problem saving the captured packets to 
	      the file you specified, it will display an error dialog box. 
	      After clicking OK on this error dialog box, you can try again. 
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Click on the Cancel button to go back to Ethereal and not save the 
	      captured packets.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</orderedlist>
      </para>
    </section>
  <section id="ChIOOutputFormatsSection">
    <title>Output File Formats</title>
    <para>
	The following file formats can be saved by <application>Ethereal</application>,
	so other capture tools can read the capture data from:
	<itemizedlist>
	      <listitem><para>libpcap (tcpdump)</para></listitem>
	      <listitem><para>Novell LANalyzer</para></listitem>
	      <listitem><para>Network Associates Sniffer</para></listitem>
	      <listitem><para>Sun snoop</para></listitem>
	      <listitem><para>Microsoft Network Monitor</para></listitem>
	      <listitem><para>Visual Networks Visual UpTime traffic</para></listitem>
	      <listitem><para>Accellent 5Views</para></listitem>
	      <listitem><para>Networks Instruments Observer version 9</para></listitem>
	      <listitem><para>HP-UX's nettl</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
    </para>
	<note><title></title>
	<para>
	Other protocol analyzers may require that the file has a certain suffix 
	in order to read the files you generate with Ethereal, e.g.:
	</para>
	<para>
	".DMP" for Tcpdump/libpcap
	</para>
	<para>
	".CAP" for Network Associates Sniffer Windows
	</para>
	</note>
  </section>	
  </section>
  
  <section id="ChIOMergeSection"><title>Merging capture files</title>
	<para>
	Sometimes you need to merge several capture files into one. For example 
	this can be useful, if you have captured simultaneously from multiple 
	interfaces at once (e.g. using multiple instances of Ethereal).
	</para>
	<para>
	Merging capture files can be done in three ways:
	<itemizedlist>
		<listitem><para>
		Use the <command>menu item "Merge"</command> from the "File" menu, 
		to open the merge dialog, see <xref linkend="ChIOMergeDialog"/>.
		This menu item will be disabled, until you have loaded a capture file.
		</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>
	  	Use <command>drag-and-drop</command> to drop multiple files on the 
		main window. Ethereal will try to merge the packets in chronological 
		order from the dropped files into a newly created temporary file. If 
		you drop only a single file, it will simply replace a (maybe) existing
		one.
		</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>
	  	Use the <command>mergecap</command> tool, which is a command 
		line tool to merge capture files. This tool provides the most options 
		to merge capture files, see <xref linkend="AppToolsmergecap"/>.
		</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	</para>
	<section><title>The "Merge with Capture File" dialog box</title>
	<para>
	This dialog box let you select a file to be merged into the currently 
	loaded file.
	</para>
	<note><title>Note!</title>
	<para>If your current data wasn't saved before, you will be asked to save 
	it first, before this dialog box is shown.</para>
	</note>
	<figure id="ChIOMergeDialog">
      <title>The "Merge with Capture File" dialog box</title>
      <graphic entityref="EtherealMergeDialog" format="PNG"/>
    </figure>
	<variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><command>Prepend packets to existing file</command></term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
		Prepend the packets from the selected file before the currently loaded 
		packets.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><command>Merge packets chronologically</command></term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
		Merge both the packets from the selected and currently loaded file in 
		chronological order.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><command>Append packets to existing file</command></term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
		Append the packets from the selected file after the currently loaded 
		packets.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	</variablelist>
	<para>
	All other controls will work the same way as in the "Open Capture File" 
	dialog box, see <xref linkend="ChIOOpen"/>.
	</para>
	</section>
  </section>
  
  <section id="ChIOFileSetSection"><title>File Sets</title>
    <para>
      When using the "Multiple Files" option while doing a capture
	  (see: <xref linkend="ChCapCaptureFiles"/>), 
	  the capture data is spreaded over several capture files, called a file 
	  set. 
    </para>
    <para>
	  As it can become tedious to work with a file set by hand, Ethereal 
	  provides some features to handle these file sets in a convenient way.
    </para>
    <sidebar><title>How does Ethereal detect the files of a file set?</title>
    <para>
	  A filename in a file set uses the format Prefix_Number_DateTimeSuffix 
	  which might look like this: "test_00001_20060420183910.pcap".
	  All files of a file set share the same prefix (e.g. "test") and suffix 
	  (e.g. ".pcap") and a varying middle part.
    </para>
    <para>
	  To find the files of a file set, Ethereal scans the directory where the 
	  currently loaded file resides and scans for files matching the same filename 
	  pattern (prefix and suffix) than the currently loaded file. 
    </para>
    <para>
	  This simple mechanism usually works well, but has it's drawbacks. If several 
	  file sets were captured with the same prefix and suffix, Ethereal will detect 
	  them as a single file set. If files were renamed or spreaded over several 
	  directories the mechanism will fail to find all files of a set.
    </para>
	</sidebar>
    <para>
	  The following features in the "File Set" submenu of the "File" menu are 
	  available to work with file sets in a convenient way:
    </para>
	<itemizedlist>
		<listitem><para>
		The <command>List Files</command> dialog box will list the files 
		Ethereal has recognized as being part of the current file set.
		</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>
		<command>Next File</command> closes the current and opens the next 
		file in the file set.
		</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>
		<command>Previous File</command> closes the current and opens the 
		previous file in the file set.
		</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	<section id="ChIOFileSetListDialog">
	<title>The "List Files" dialog box</title>
    <figure>
      <title>The "List Files" dialog box</title>
      <graphic entityref="EtherealFileSetDialog" format="PNG"/>
    </figure>
	  <para>
	  Each line contains information about a file of the file set:
	<itemizedlist>
		<listitem><para>
		<command>Filename</command> the name of the file. If you click on 
		the filename (or the radio button left to it), the current file will
		be closed and the corresponding capture file will be opened. 
		</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>
		<command>Created</command> the creation time of the file
		</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>
		<command>Last Modified</command> the last time the file was modified
		</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>
		<command>Size</command> the size of the file
		</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	  The last line will contain info about the currently used directory where
	  all of the files in the file set can be found.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	  The content of this dialog box is updated each time a capture file is 
	  opened/closed.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	  The Close button will, well, close the dialog box.
	  </para>
	</section>
  </section>
  <section id="ChIOExportSection"><title>Exporting data</title>
    <para>
      Ethereal provides several ways and formats to export packet data. This 
	  section describes general ways to export data from Ethereal.
    </para>
	<note><title>Note!</title>
	<para>
	  There are more specialized functions to export specific data, 
	  which will be described at the appropriate places. 
	</para>
	</note>
    <para>
	  XXX - add detailed descriptions of the output formats and some sample 
	  output, too.
    </para>
	<section id="ChIOExportPlainDialog">
	<title>The "Export as Plain Text File" dialog box</title>
	  <para id="ChIOExportPlain">
	    Export packet data into a plain ASCII text file, much like the format 
		used to print packets.
    <figure>
      <title>The "Export as Plain Text File" dialog box</title>
      <graphic entityref="EtherealExportPlainDialog" format="PNG"/>
    </figure>
	<itemizedlist>
		<listitem><para>
	  	<command>Export to file:</command> frame chooses the file to export 
		the packet data to.
		</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>
	  	The <command>Packet Range</command> frame is described in <xref 
		linkend="ChIOPacketRangeSection"/>.
		</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>
	  	The <command>Packet Details</command> frame is described in <xref 
		linkend="ChIOPacketFormatSection"/>.
		</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>	
	  </para>
    </section>
	<section id="ChIOExportPSDialog">
	<title>The "Export as PostScript File" dialog box</title>
	  <para>
	    Export packet data into PostScript, much like the format used 
		to print packets.
	<tip><title>Tip!</title>
	<para>
	You can easily convert PostScript files to PDF files using ghostscript.
	For example: export to a file named foo.ps and then call: 
	<command>ps2pdf foo.ps</command>
	</para>
	</tip>
    <figure>
      <title>The "Export as PostScript File" dialog box</title>
      <graphic entityref="EtherealExportPSDialog" format="PNG"/>
    </figure>
	<itemizedlist>
		<listitem><para>
	  	<command>Export to file:</command> frame chooses the file to export 
		the packet data to.
		</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>
	  	The <command>Packet Range</command> frame is described in <xref 
		linkend="ChIOPacketRangeSection"/>.
		</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>
	  	The <command>Packet Details</command> frame is described in <xref 
		linkend="ChIOPacketFormatSection"/>.
		</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>	
	  </para>
    </section>
	<section id="ChIOExportCSVDialog">
	<title>The "Export as CSV (Comma Seperated Values) File" dialog box</title>
	  <para>XXX - add screenshot</para>
	  <para>
	    Export packet summary into CSV, used e.g. by spreadsheet programs to 
		im-/export data.
    <!--<figure>
      <title>The "Export as Comma Seperated Values File" dialog box</title>
      <graphic entityref="EtherealExportCSVDialog" format="PNG"/>
    </figure>-->
	<itemizedlist>
		<listitem><para>
	  	<command>Export to file:</command> frame chooses the file to export 
		the packet data to.
		</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>
	  	The <command>Packet Range</command> frame is described in <xref 
		linkend="ChIOPacketRangeSection"/>.
		</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>	
	  </para>
    </section>
	<section id="ChIOExportPSMLDialog">
	<title>The "Export as PSML File" dialog box</title>
	  <para>
	    Export packet data into PSML. This is an XML based format including 
		only the packet summary.
    <figure>
      <title>The "Export as PSML File" dialog box</title>
      <graphic entityref="EtherealExportPSMLDialog" format="PNG"/>
    </figure>
	<itemizedlist>
		<listitem><para>
	  	<command>Export to file:</command> frame chooses the file to export 
		the packet data to.
		</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>
	  	The <command>Packet Range</command> frame is described in <xref 
		linkend="ChIOPacketRangeSection"/>.
		</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>	
	There's no such thing as a packet details frame for PSML export, as the 
	packet format is defined by the PSML specification.
	  </para>
    </section>
	<section id="ChIOExportPDMLDialog">
	<title>The "Export as PDML File" dialog box</title>
	  <para>
	    Export packet data into PDML. This is an XML based format including 
		the packet details. The PDML file specification is available at: 
		<ulink url="http://analyzer.polito.it/30alpha/docs/dissectors/PDMLSpec.htm">
		PDML specification</ulink>.
		<note><title></title>
		<para>
		The PDML specification is not officially released and Ethereal's 
		implementation of it is still in an early beta state, so please expect 
		changes in future Ethereal versions.
		</para>
		</note>
    <figure>
      <title>The "Export as PDML File" dialog box</title>
      <graphic entityref="EtherealExportPDMLDialog" format="PNG"/>
    </figure>
	<itemizedlist>
		<listitem><para>
	  	<command>Export to file:</command> frame chooses the file to export 
		the packet data to.
		</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>
	  	The <command>Packet Range</command> frame is described in <xref 
		linkend="ChIOPacketRangeSection"/>.
		</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>	
	There's no such thing as a packet details frame for PDML export, as the 
	packet format is defined by the PDML specification.
	  </para>
  </section>
	<section id="ChIOExportSelectedDialog">
	<title>The "Export selected packet bytes" dialog box</title>
	  <para>
	    Export the bytes selected in the "Packet Bytes" pane into a raw 
		binary file.
    <figure>
      <title>The "Export Selected Packet Bytes" dialog box</title>
      <graphic entityref="EtherealExportSelectedDialog" format="PNG"/>
    </figure>
	<itemizedlist>
		<listitem><para>
	  	<command>Name:</command> the filename to export the packet data to.
		</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>
	  	The <command>Save in folder:</command> field lets you select the 
		folder to save to (from some predefined folders).
		</para></listitem>
		<listitem><para>
	  	<command>Browse for other folders</command> provides a flexible 
		way to choose a folder.
		</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>	
	  </para>
  </section>
  </section>

  <section id="ChIOPrintSection"><title>Printing packets</title>
    <para>
	    To print packets, select the "Print..." menu item from the File menu. 
		When you do this, Ethereal pops up the Print dialog box as shown in 
	    <xref linkend="ChIOPrintDialogBox"/>.
    </para>
	<section><title>The "Print" dialog box</title>
    <figure id="ChIOPrintDialogBox">
      <title>The "Print" dialog box</title>
      <graphic entityref="EtherealPrint" format="PNG"/>
    </figure>
    <para>
      The following fields are available in the Print dialog box:
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry><term><command>Printer</command></term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      This field contains a pair of mutually exclusive radio buttons:
	      <itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    <command>Plain Text</command> specifies that 
		    the packet print should be in plain text.
		  </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    <command>PostScript</command> specifies that 
		    the packet print process should use PostScript to 
		    generate a better print output on PostScript aware printers.
		  </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    <command>Output to file:</command> specifies that printing 
		    be done to a file, which name is entered in the field or selected 
			using the browse button.
		  </para>
	    <para>
	      This field is where you enter the <command>file</command> to 
	      print to if you have selected Print to a file, or you can click the 
		  button to browse the filesystem. It is greyed out if Print to a file 
		  is not selected.
	    </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    <command>Print command</command> specifies that a 
		    command be used for printing. 
		  </para>
		<note><title>Note!</title>
		<para>
		These <command>Print command</command> fields are not available on 
		windows platforms. 
		</para>
		</note>
	    <para>
	      This field specifies the command to use for printing. It 
	      is typically <command>lpr</command>. You would change it 
	      to specify a particular queue if you need to print to a 
	      queue other than the default.  An example might be:
	      <programlisting>
lpr -Pmypostscript
	      </programlisting>
	      This field is greyed out if <command>Output to file:</command> is 
	      checked above.
	    </para>
		</listitem>
	      </itemizedlist>
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><command>Packet Range</command></term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
		  Select the packets to be printed, see <xref 
		  linkend="ChIOPacketRangeSection"/>
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><command>Packet Format</command></term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
		  Select the output format of the packets to be printed. You can 
		  choose, how each packet is printed, see 
		  <xref linkend="ChIOPacketFormatFrame"/>
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
  </section>
  </section>

  <section id="ChIOPacketRangeSection"><title>The Packet Range frame</title>
	<para>
	The packet range frame is a part of various output related dialog boxes. 
	It provides options to select which packets should be processed by the 
	output function.
    <figure id="ChIOPacketRangeFrame">
      <title>The "Packet Range" frame</title>
      <graphic entityref="EtherealPacketRangeFrame" format="PNG"/>
    </figure>
	</para>
	<para>
	If the <command>Captured</command> button is set (default), all packets 
	from the selected rule will be processed. If the <command>Displayed
	</command> button is set, only the currently displayed packets are taken 
	into account to the selected rule.
	</para>
	<para>
	<itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		  <command>All packets</command> will process all packets.
		  </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		  <command>Selected packet only</command> process only the selected 
		  packet.
		  </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		  <command>Marked packets only</command> process only the marked 
		  packets.
		  </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		  <command>From first to last marked packet</command> process the 
		  packets from the first to the last marked one.
		  </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		  <command>Specify a packet range</command> process a user specified 
		  range of packets, e.g. specifying <command>5,10-15,20-</command> will 
		  process the packet number five, the packets from packet number ten 
		  to fifteen (inclusive) and every packet from number twenty to the 
		  end of the capture.
		  </para>
		</listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	</para>
  </section>
  
  <section id="ChIOPacketFormatSection"><title>The Packet Format frame</title>
	<para>
	The packet format frame is a part of various output related dialog boxes. 
	It provides options to select which parts of a packet should be used for 
	the output function.
    <figure id="ChIOPacketFormatFrame">
      <title>The "Packet Format" frame</title>
      <graphic entityref="EtherealPacketFormatFrame" format="PNG"/>
    </figure>
	<itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		  <command>Packet summary line</command> enable the output of the 
		  summary line, just as in the "Packet List" pane.
		  </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		  <command>Packet details</command> enable the output of the packet 
		  details tree.
		  </para>
		<itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		  <command>All collapsed</command> the info from the "Packet Details" 
		  pane in "all collapsed" state.
		  </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		  <command>As displayed</command> the info from the "Packet Details" 
		  pane in the current state.
		  </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		  <command>All expanded</command> the info from the "Packet Details" 
		  pane in "all expanded" state.
		  </para>
		</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		  <command>Packet bytes</command> enable the output of the packet 
		  bytes, just as in the "Packet Bytes" pane.
		  </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		  <command>Each packet on a new page</command> put each packet on a 
		  separate page (e.g. when saving/printing to a text file, this will 
		  put a form feed character between the packets).
		  </para>
		</listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	</para>
  </section>
  
</chapter>
<!-- End of EUG Chapter IO -->

