<!-- EDG Chapter Works -->
<!-- $Id: EDG_chapter_works.xml 11908 2004-09-05 21:22:14Z ulfl $ -->

<chapter id="ChapterWorks">
  <title>How Ethereal Works</title>
  
  <section id="ChWorksIntro">
	<title>Introduction</title>
	<para>
	This chapter will give you a short overview, how Ethereal is working.
	</para>

	<section id="ChWorksCapturePackets">
	<title>Capturing packets</title>
	<para>
	Capturing will take packets from a network adapter, and save them to a file 
	on your harddisk. 
	</para>
	<para>
	To hide all the lowlevel machine dependant details from 
	Ethereal, the libpcap/WinPcap (see <xref linkend="ChLibsPcap"/>) library 
	is used. This library provides a general purpose interface to capture 
	packets from a lot of different network interface types (Ethernet, 
	Token Ring, ...). 
	</para>
	</section>

	<section id="ChWorksCaptureFiles">
	<title>Capture Files</title>
	<para>
	Ethereal can read and write capture files in it's natural file format, the 
	libpcap format, which is used by many other network capturing tools, 
	e.g. tcpdump. In addition to this, as one of it's strengths,
	Ethereal can read/write files in many different file formats of other 
	network capturing tools. The wiretap library, developed together with 
	Ethereal, provides a general purpose interface to read/write all the file 
	formats. If you need to add another capture file format, this is the place 
	to start.	
	</para>
	</section>

	<section id="ChWorksDissectPackets">
	<title>Dissect packets</title>
	<para>
	While Ethereal is loading packets from a file, each packet is dissected. 
	Ethereal tries to detect what kind of packet it is and getting as much 
	information from it as possible. In this run, only the information showed 
	in the packet list pane is needed though. 
	</para>
	<para>
	As the user selects a specific packet in the packet list pane, this packet
	will be dissected again. This time, Ethereal tries to 
	get every single piece of information and put it into 
	the packet details pane then.
	</para>
	</section>

  </section>
</chapter>
<!-- End of EUG Chapter Works -->
