<!-- EDG Chapter Introduction -->
<!-- $Id$ -->

<chapter id="ChapterIntroduction">
  <title>Introduction</title>
  <!-- Introduction -->
  <section id="ChIntroWhatIs">
    <title>What is <application>Ethereal?</application></title>
    <para>
	Well, if you want to develop some things into Ethereal, you might already 
	know what Ethereal is doing. If not, please have a look at the 
	<ulink url="&EtherealUsersGuidePage;">Ethereal User's Guide</ulink>, 
	which will explain what Ethereal is doing and a lot more general 
	information about it.
    </para>
		
	<section><title>Open Source Software</title>
    <para>
      Ethereal is an open source software project, and is released under 
      the <ulink url="&GPLWebsite;">GNU General Public Licence</ulink> (GPL). 
	  You can freely use Ethereal on any number of computers you like, without 
	  worrying about license keys or fees or such. In addition, all source 
	  code is freely available under the GPL. Because of that, it is very easy 
	  for people to add new protocols to Ethereal, either as plugins, or built 
	  into the source, and they often do!
    </para>
	</section>
	
  </section>
  
  <section id="ChIntroDevelopment">
    <title>Ethereal development</title>
    <para>
	The Ethereal development is done by the Ethereal developer community, a 
	loosely coupled group of persons interested in network analyzing. The 
	communication between the developers is usually done trough the developer 
	mailing list, which can be joined by anyone interested in the development 
	process. At the time writing of this document, more than 500 persons are 
	subscribed to this mailing list!
    </para>
    <para>
	Ethereal is implemented in plain ANSI C. As it's developed in a platform 
	independant way and uses a platform independant GUI library (GTK+), it's 
	available on a wide variety of platforms.
    </para>
    <para>
	Beside the usual tools for developing a program in C (compiler, make, ...), 
	the build process uses some additional helper tools (Perl, Python, Sed, 
	...), which are needed for the build process and in the case Ethereal 
	should be installed from the released source packages. If Ethereal is 
	installed from a binary package, none of these helper tools are needed on 
	the target system.
	</para>
  </section>	
	
  <section id="ChIntroPlatforms">
    <title>Platforms Ethereal runs on</title>
    <para>
      Ethereal currently runs on most UNIX platforms and various Windows 
      platforms. It requires GTK+, GLib, libpcap and some other libraries in 
	  order to run.
    </para>
    <para>
      If a binary package is not available for your platform, you should 
      download the source and try to build it. Please report your experiences
	  to <ulink url="mailto:&EtherealDevMailList;">&EtherealDevMailList;</ulink>.
    </para>
    <para>
      Binary packages are available for at least the following platforms:
    </para>

	<section><title>Unix</title>
	<para>
	<itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>Apple Mac OS X</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>BeOS</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>FreeBSD</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>HP-UX</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>IBM AIX</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>NetBSD</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>OpenBSD</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>SCO UnixWare/OpenUnix</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>SGI Irix</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Sun Solaris/Intel</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Sun Solaris/Sparc</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Tru64 UNIX (formerly Digital UNIX)</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	</para>
	</section>
	
	<section><title>Linux</title>
	<para>
	<itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>Debian GNU/Linux</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Gentoo Linux</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>IBM S/390 Linux (Red Hat)</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Mandrake Linux</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>PLD Linux</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Red Hat Linux</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Rock Linux</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Slackware Linux</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Suse Linux</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	</para>
	</section>
	
	<section><title>Microsoft Windows</title>
    <para>
	<itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>Windows Me / 98 / 95</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Windows Server 2003 / XP / 2000 / NT 4.0</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	Thanks to the Win32 API, development on all windows platforms will be 
	done in a very similar way. However some differences between the platforms 
	are existing (especially between the NT and 95 based platforms), the 
	differences will be notified where appropriate. All Windows platforms will 
	be referred as Win32, Win or Windows might be used with the same meaning.
    </para>
	</section>
	
  </section>
  
  <section id="ChIntroReleases">
    <title>Releases and distributions</title>
    <para>
	The officially released files can be found at: <ulink 
	url="&EtherealDownloadPage;"/>. A new Ethereal version is released, after 
	significant changes compared to the last release were completed or a 
	serious security issue was encountered. The typical release schedule is
	about every 4-8 weeks (although this may vary).
    </para>
    <para>
	There are two kinds of distributions: binary and source, both have their 
	advantages and disadvantages. As it's still very common for unix programs 
	to give the end user a source tarball and let the user compile it on 
	their target machine, this is very uncommon for win32 end users.
    </para>

	<section id="ChIntroReleaseBinary">
    <title>Binary distributions</title>
    <para>
	Binary distributions are usually easy to install (as simply starting
	the appropriate file is usually the only thing to do). They are available 
	for the following systems:
	<itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
    <para>
	Win32 (.exe file)
    </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
    <para>
	Debian (.deb file)
    </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
    <para>
	RedHat (.rpm file)
    </para>
	</listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	However, if you want to start developing with Ethereal, the binary
	distributions won't be much helpful, as you need the source files, of
	course.
    </para>
	</section>

	<section id="ChIntroReleaseSource">
	<title>Source code distributions</title>
    <para>
	You should use the released sources if you want to build Ethereal from
	source on your platform for productive use. However, if you want to 
	develop changes to the Ethereal sources, it might be better to use the 
	latest SVN sources, the reasons for this will be explained later in this 
	document.
    </para>
    <para>
	Before building Ethereal from a source distribution, make sure you have
	all the tools and libraries required to build. The next chapters will
	describe the required tools and libraries in detail.
    </para>
	</section>
  </section>
  
  <section id="ChIntroDownload">
    <title>Where to get Ethereal?</title>
    <para>
      You can get the latest copy of the program from the Ethereal website: 
      <ulink url="&EtherealDownloadPage;">&EtherealDownloadPage;</ulink>.  The 
      website allows you to choose from among several mirrors for 
      downloading.
    </para>
    <para>
	A new Ethereal version will typically become available every 4-8 weeks.
    </para>
  </section>
      
  <section id="ChIntroMaintenance">
    <title>
      Development and maintenance of <application>Ethereal</application>
    </title>
    <para>
      Ethereal was initially developed by Gerald Combs. Ongoing development 
      and maintenance of Ethereal is handled by the Ethereal team, a loose 
      group of individuals who fix bugs and provide new functionality.  
    </para>
    <para>
      There have also been a large number of people who have contributed 
      protocol dissectors to Ethereal, and it is expected that this will 
      continue.  You can find a list of the people who have contributed 
      code to Ethereal by checking the about dialog box of Ethereal, or at 
	  the <ulink url="&EtherealAuthorsPage;">authors</ulink> page on the 
      Ethereal web site.
    </para>
    <para>
      Ethereal is an open source software project, and is released under 
      the <ulink url="&GPLWebsite;">GNU General Public Licence</ulink> (GPL). 
	  All source code is freely available under the GPL. You are welcome to 
      modify Ethereal to suit your own needs, and it would be appreciated 
      if you contribute your improvements back to the Ethereal team.
    </para>
    <para>
      You gain three benefits by contributing your improvements back to the 
      community:
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Other people who find your contributions useful will appreciate 
	    them, and you will know that you have helped people in the 
	    same way that the developers of Ethereal have helped people.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    The developers of Ethereal might improve your changes even more,
		as there's always room for improvements. Or they may implement some 
		advanced things on top of your code, which can be useful for yourself
		too.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    The maintainers and developers of Ethereal will maintain your 
	    code as well, fixing it when API changes or other changes are 
	    made, and generally keeping it in tune with what is happening 
	    with Ethereal. So if Ethereal is updated (which is done often),
		you can get a new Ethereal version from the website and your changes 
		will already be included without any effort for you.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    <para>
      The Ethereal source code and binary kits for some platforms are all 
      available on the download page of the Ethereal website: 
      <ulink url="&EtherealDownloadPage;">&EtherealDownloadPage;</ulink>.
    </para>
  </section>
  
  <section id="ChIntroHelp">
    <title>Reporting problems and getting help</title>
	<para>
      If you have problems, or need help with Ethereal, there are several 
      places that may be of interest to you (well, beside this guide of 
	  course).
	</para>
	
	<section id="ChIntroFAQ"><title>FAQ</title>
    <para>
	The "Frequently Asked Questions" will list often asked questions and 
	the corresponding answers.
	<note><title>Read the FAQ!</title>
	<para>
	Before sending any mail to the mailing lists below, be sure to read the 
	FAQ, as it will often answer the question(s) you might have. This will save 
	yourself and others a lot of time (keep in mind that a lot of people are 
	subscribed to the mailing lists). 
    </para>
    </note>
	You will find the FAQ inside Ethereal by clicking the menu item 
	Help/Contents and selecting the FAQ page in the upcoming dialog. 
    </para>
    <para>
	An online version is available at the ethereal website:
	<ulink url="&EtherealFAQPage;">&EtherealFAQPage;</ulink>. You might 
	prefer this online version, as it's typically more up to date and the HTML 
	format is easier to use.
    </para>
	</section>
	
	<section id="ChIntroMailingLists"><title>Mailing Lists</title>
    <para>
      There are several mailing lists of specific Ethereal topics available:
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry><term><command>ethereal-announce</command></term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      This mailing list will inform you about new program 
		  releases, which usually appear about every 4-8 weeks.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry><term><command>ethereal-users</command></term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      This list is for users of Ethereal.  People post 
	      questions about building and using Ethereal, others (hopefully) 
		  provide answers. 
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry><term><command>ethereal-dev</command></term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      This list is for Ethereal developers. If you want to start 
	      developing a protocol dissector, join this list.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
      You can subscribe to each of these lists from the Ethereal web site: 
      <ulink url="&EtherealWebSite;">&EtherealWebSite;</ulink>.  Simply 
      select the <command>mailing lists</command> link on the left hand 
      side of the site. The lists are archived at the Ethereal web site 
      as well.
	<tip><title>Tip!</title>
	<para>
	You can search in the list archives to see if someone asked the same 
	question some time before and maybe already got an answer. That way you 
	don't have to wait until someone answers your question.
	</para>
	</tip>
    </para>
	</section>
	
	<section><title>Reporting Problems</title>
	<note><title>Note!</title>
	<para>
	Before reporting any problems, please make sure you have installed the 
	latest version of Ethereal.
	</para>
	</note>
    <para>
      When reporting problems with Ethereal, it is helpful if you supply the 
      following information:
      <orderedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    The version number of Ethereal and the dependent libraries linked with 
		it, eg GTK+, etc. You can obtain this with the command 
	    <command>ethereal -v</command>.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Information about the platform you run Ethereal on.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    A detailed description of your problem.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </para>
	<note><title>Don't send large files!</title>
	<para>
	Do not send large files (>100KB) to the mailing lists, just place a note 
	that further data is available on request. Large files will only annoy a 
	lot of people on the list who are not interested in your specific problem. 
	If required, you will be asked for further data by the persons who really 
	can help you.
	</para>
	</note>
	<note><title>Don't send confidential information!</title>
	<para>
	If you send captured data to the mailing lists, be sure they don't contain 
	any sensitive or confidential information like passwords or such.
	</para>
	</note>
  </section>
  
	<section><title>Reporting Crashes on UNIX/Linux platforms</title>
    <para>
      When reporting crashes with Ethereal, it is helpful if you supply the 
      traceback information (besides the information mentioned in "Reporting 
	  Problems").
    </para>
	  <para>
	    You can obtain this traceback information with the following commands:
	    <programlisting>
<![CDATA[
$ gdb `whereis ethereal | cut -f2 -d: | cut -d' ' -f2` core >& bt.txt
backtrace
^D
$
]]>
		</programlisting>
	    <note>
	      <para>
		Type the characters in the first line verbatim! Those are 
		back-tics there!
	      </para>
	    </note>
	    <note>
	      <para>
		backtrace is a <command>gdb</command> command. You should 
		enter it verbatim after the first line shown above, but it will not be 
		echoed. The ^D 
		(Control-D, that is, press the Control key and the D key 
		together) will cause <command>gdb</command> to exit. This will 
		leave you with a file called 
		<filename>bt.txt</filename> in the current directory. 
		Include the file with your bug report.
	      </para>
	    </note>
	    <note>
	      <para>
		If you do not have <command>gdb</command> available, you 
		will have to check out your operating system's debugger.  
	      </para>
	    </note>
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    You should mail the traceback to the 
		<ulink url="mailto:&EtherealDevMailList;">&EtherealDevMailList;</ulink>
	    mailing list.
	  </para>
  </section>
  
	<section><title>Reporting Crashes on Windows platforms</title>
    <para>
	The Windows distributions don't contain the symbol files (.pdb), because 
	they are very large. For this reason it's not possible to create 
	a meaningful backtrace file from it. You should report your crash just
	like other problems, using the mechanism described above.
    </para>
  </section>
  </section>

  <section><title>Other sources of information</title>
    <para>
	There are various other sources of information for Ethereal developers:
	<itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	<para>
    have a look at the Ethereal source code
	</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	<para>
    there are various documentation files inside the source code, see the README.xxx files
	</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	<para>
    tool documentation of the various tools used (e.g. manpages of sed, gcc, ...)
	</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	<para>
    the developer mailing list <ulink url="&EtherealDevMailList;"/>
	</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	<para>
    ...
	</para>
	</listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
    </para>
  </section>

</chapter>
<!-- End of EUG Chapter 1 -->
