<!-- WSUG Appendix How it Works -->

<appendix id="AppHowItWorks">
  <title>How Wireshark Works</title>
  <para>
  When using such a complex program like Wireshark, it's sometimes useful to 
  understand the mechanisms and concepts behind the surface. This is an 
  approach to shed some light on the inner workings of Wireshark.
  </para>

  <section><title>Program start</title>
  <para>
  When Wireshark starts, a lot of things are done:
  <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
  initialize the dissectors (register the protocol tree), including plugins
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
  load and set values from the preferences file
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
  load the capture filters from the cfilters file
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
  load the display filters from the dfilters file
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
  load and set the disabled protocols from the disabled_protos file
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
  init libpcap/winpcap (the capturing engine)
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
  process command line parameters
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
  load and set the recently used GUI settings from the recent file
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
  init and show the main screen
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
  if specified by command line, load a capture file or start capturing
  </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  </para>
  <para>
  
  </para>
  </section>

  <section><title>Protocol dissectors</title>
  <para>
  Each protocol has its own protocol dissector. A dissector is called from 
  Wireshark, if the packet data seems to be of that corresponding protocol. The 
  dissector  will then process the packet data and call back Wireshark if it 
  couldn't dissect all the data in that packet to do any further dissections.
  </para>
  <para>
  So Wireshark will dissect a packet from the lowest to the highest protocol 
  layers.
  </para>
  <para>
  But how does Wireshark know, which dissector to choose?
  </para>
  <para>
  At program start, the dissector registers itself at the appropriate place(s). 
  There are two ways, how a dissector can register itself for packet data:
  <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
  <command>static</command> if the dissector knows a specific value 
  of a lower layer, if can directly register itself there (e.g. the HTTP 
  dissector "knows", that typically the well known TCP port 80 is used to 
  transport HTTP data).
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
  <command>heuristic</command> if no such well known way exists, the dissector 
  can register itself for the heuristic mechanism. If a lower layer dissector 
  has to handle some packet data where no well known way exists, it can 
  handover the packet to Wireshark's heuristic mechanism. This will ask all 
  registered upper layer dissectors, if they "like" that data. Each of these 
  dissectors will typically look into the first few bytes of the packet, if it 
  contains some characteristic data of that protocol. So the dissector can 
  accept or reject to dissect that packet.
  </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  </para>
  <para>
  Let's look at an example: We'll assume, Wireshark loads a TCP/IP/Ethernet 
  packet. Wireshark will call the Ethernet dissector, which will dissect the 
  Ethernet related data (usually the first 6+6+2 bytes). Then this dissector 
  calls back into Wireshark and will pass the rest of the data back to 
  Wireshark. Wireshark in turn will call the next related dissector, in our case 
  the IP dissector (because of the value 0x800 in the Ethernet type field). 
  This game will continue, until no more data has to be dissected, or the data 
  is just unknown to Wireshark.
  </para>
  <para>
  You can control the way Wireshark calls its dissectors, see <xref 
  linkend="ChAdvProtocolDissectionSection"/> for details.
  </para>
  </section>

</appendix>
<!-- End of WSUG Appendix How it Works -->
