<!-- WSUG Chapter Four -->
<!-- $Id$ -->

<chapter id="Chap04">
  <title>Troubleshooting with <application>Wireshark</application></title>
  <section>
    <title>An approach to troubleshooting with Wireshark</title>
    <para>
      Wireshark is a very useful tool for network troubleshooting, since it 
      contains a number of features that allow you to quickly focus on 
      problems in your networkfor several reasons:
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    It allows you to focus in on specific packets and protocols, 
	    as you can see a large amount of detail associated with 
	    various protocols.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    It supports a large number of protocols, and the list of 
	    protocols supported is growing as more people contribute 
	    dissectors
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    By giving you a visual view of traffic in parts of your 
	    network, and providing tools to filter and colorize that 
	    information, you can get a better feel for your network 
	    traffic, and can understand your network better.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist> 
    </para>
    <para>
      The following general approach is suggested:
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Determine that the problem looks like a networking problem.  
	    There is no point in capturing packets if the problem is not 
	    networking related.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Figure out where to capture packets.  You will have to 
	    capture packets from a part of the network where you can 
	    actually get network traffic related to the problem.  This is 
	    especially important in the presence of switches and routers.  
	    See <xref linkend="Ch04ROUSWI"/> for more details.
	  </para>
	  <para>
	    Because Wireshark can read many capture file formats, you can 
	    capture using any conventient tool. One useful approach is 
	    to use <command>tcpdump</command> to capture on remote 
	    systems and then copy the capture file to your system for 
	    later analysis. For more details on capturing with 
	    <command>tcpdump</command>, see <xref linkend="Ch05tcpdump"/>.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Once you have captured packets that you think relate to 
	    the problem, load them into Wireshark and look for your 
	    problem. Using Wireshark's filtering and colorization 
	    capabilities, you can quickly narrow down the capture to the 
	    area of interest.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Examine the appropriate fields within the packets where 
	    the problem appears to be. These can often help to reveal 
	    the problem. 
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section id="Ch04ROUSWI">
    <title>Capturing in the presence of switches and routers</title>
    <para>
	In the old days of Ethernet, all network traffic was spreaded over one 
	"yellow" cable through the whole network. Capturing data was easy,
	as all packets from the network could be captured using the 
	"promiscuous mode" at any place in the network. The only devices blocking 
	network traffic, were routers. But as routers were extremely expensive, 
	they were not widely used.
    </para>
    <para>
	Then Ethernet wiring using hubs become the state of the art. As the hubs 
	still spreaded the packets all over the network, things regarding 
	capturing didn't changed.
    </para>
    <para>
	At the next stage, Ethernet switches became widely available. This 
	complicated things a lot. When capturing traffic on a computer connected 
	to a switch, usually the switch will only forward packets to the computer, 
	which are directed to it, or to all computers (broadcast's). It's much the 
	same like deactivating the promiscuous mode of the capturing network card.
    </para>
    <para>
	There are some ways to circumvent this.
    </para>
    <para>
      Many vendor's switches support a feature known as "port spanning" 
      or "port mirroring" in which all of the traffic to and from port A 
      are also sent out port B.  An excellent reference on the 
      "port spanning" feature of Cisco switches can be found at 
      <ulink url="http://www.cisco.com/warp/public/473/41.html">
	Configuring the Catalyst Switched Port Analyzer (SPAN) Feature
      </ulink>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Examples of troubleshooting</title>
    <para>
      Troubleshooting often requires a reasonable knowledge of the 
      protocols in question. However, as Wireshark will often give you some 
	  good hints, you might get an idea of what is going wrong simply by 
	  looking in the packets being exchanged.
    </para>
  </section>
</chapter>
<!-- End of WSUG Chapter 4 -->

