<!-- WSUG Chapter Statistics -->

<chapter id="ChStatistics">
  <title>Statistics</title>
  <section id="ChStatIntroduction">
  <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>
    Wireshark provides a wide range of network statistics which can be accessed via the
    <command>Statistics</command> menu.
    </para>
    <para>
    These statistics range from general information about the loaded capture file
    (like the number of captured packets), to statistics about specific protocols
    (e.g. statistics about the number of HTTP requests and responses captured).
    <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
    <para>
    General statistics:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
    <para><command>Summary</command> about the capture file.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
    <para><command>Protocol Hierarchy</command> of the captured packets.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
    <para><command>Conversations</command> e.g. traffic between specific IP
    addresses.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
    <para><command>Endpoints</command> e.g. traffic to and from an IP
    addresses.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
    <para><command>IO Graphs</command> visualizing the number of packets (or
    similar) in time.</para>
    </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
    <para>
    Protocol specific statistics:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
    <para><command>Service Response Time</command> between request and response
    of some protocols.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
    <para><command>Various other</command> protocol specific statistics.</para>
    </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <note><title>Note!</title>
    <para>
    The protocol specific statistics requires detailed knowledge about the
    specific protocol. Unless you are familiar with that protocol, statistics
    about it will be pretty hard to understand.
    </para>
    </note>
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="ChStatSummary">
    <title>The "Summary" window</title>
    <para>
    General statistics about the current capture file.
    </para>
    <figure><title>The "Summary" window</title>
      <graphic entityref="WiresharkStatsSummary" format="PNG"/>
    </figure>
    <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
    <para><command>File</command>: general information about the capture file.
    </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
    <para><command>Time</command>: the timestamps when the first and the
    last packet were captured (and the time between them).</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
    <para><command>Capture</command>: information from the time when the
    capture was done (only available if the packet data was captured from the
    network and not loaded from a file).</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
    <para><command>Display</command>: some display related information.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
    <para>
    <command>Traffic</command>: some statistics of the network traffic seen.
    If a display filter is set, you will see values in the Captured column,
    and if any packages are marked, you will see values in the Marked column.
    The values in the <command>Captured</command> column will remain the same as
    before, while the values in the <command>Displayed</command> column will
    reflect the values corresponding to the packets shown in the display.
    The values in the <command>Marked</command> column will reflect the values
    corresponding to the marked packages.
    </para>
    </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section id="ChStatHierarchy">
    <title>The "Protocol Hierarchy" window</title>
    <para>
    The protocol hierarchy of the captured packets.
    <figure><title>The "Protocol Hierarchy" window</title>
      <graphic entityref="WiresharkStatsHierarchy" format="PNG"/>
    </figure>
    This is a tree of all the protocols in the capture. You can collapse or
    expand subtrees, by clicking on the plus / minus icons. By default, all
    trees are expanded.
    </para>
    <para>
    Each row contains the statistical values of one protocol.
    The <command>Display filter</command> will show the current display filter.
    </para>
    <para>
    The following columns containing the statistical values are available:
    <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
    <para><command>Protocol</command>: this protocol's name</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
    <para><command>% Packets</command>: the percentage of protocol packets,
    relative to all packets in the capture</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
    <para><command>Packets</command>: the absolute number of packets of this
    protocol</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
    <para><command>Bytes</command>: the absolute number of bytes of this
    protocol</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
    <para><command>MBit/s</command>: the bandwidth of this protocol, relative
    to the capture time</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
    <para>
    <command>End Packets</command>: the absolute number of packets of this
    protocol (where this protocol was the highest protocol to decode)
    </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
    <para>
    <command>End Bytes</command>: the absolute number of bytes of this protocol
    (where this protocol was the highest protocol to decode)
    </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
    <para>
    <command>End MBit/s</command>: the bandwidth of this protocol, relative to
    the capture time (where this protocol was the highest protocol to decode)
    </para>
    </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    <note><title>Note!</title>
    <para>
    Packets will usually contain multiple protocols, so more than one protocol
    will be counted for each packet.
    Example: In the screenshot IP has 99,17% and TCP 85,83% (which is together
    much more than 100%).
    </para>
    </note>
    <note><title>Note!</title>
    <para>
    Protocol layers can consist of packets that won't contain any higher layer
    protocol, so the sum of all higher layer packets may not sum up to the
    protocols packet count.
    Example: In the screenshot TCP has 85,83% but the sum of the subprotocols
    (HTTP, ...) is much less. This may be caused by TCP protocol overhead,
    e.g. TCP ACK packets won't be counted as packets of the higher layer).
    </para>
    </note>
    <note><title>Note!</title>
    <para>
    A single packet can contain the same protocol more than once. In this case,
    the protocol is counted more than once. For example: in some tunneling
    configurations the IP layer can appear twice.
    </para>
    </note>
  </section>

  <section id="ChStatConversations">
    <title>Conversations</title>
    <para>
      Statistics of the captured conversations.
    </para>
    <section>
      <title>What is a Conversation?</title>
      <para>
    A network conversation is the traffic between two specific endpoints. For
    example, an IP conversation is all the traffic between two IP addresses.
    The description of the known endpoint types can be found in
    <xref linkend="ChStatEndpointDefinition"/>.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section id="ChStatConversationsWindow"><title>The "Conversations" window</title>
    <para>
      The conversations window is similar to the
      endpoint Window; see <xref linkend="ChStatEndpointsWindow"/> for a
      description of their common features. Along with addresses, packet
      counters, and byte counters the conversation window adds four columns: the time in seconds between the start of the capture and the start of the conversation ("Rel Start"), the duration of the conversation in seconds, and the average bits (not bytes) per second in each direction.
      <figure><title>The "Conversations" window</title>
      <graphic entityref="WiresharkStatsConversations" format="PNG"/>
      </figure>
    </para>
    <para>
      Each row in the list shows the statistical values for exactly one conversation.
    </para>
    <para>
      <command>Name resolution</command> will be done if selected in the window
      and if it is active for the specific protocol layer (MAC layer for the
      selected Ethernet endpoints page).
    </para>
    <para>
      <command>Limit to display filter</command> will only show conversations matching
      the current display filter.
    </para>
    <para>
      The <command>copy</command> button will copy the list values to the
      clipboard in CSV (Comma Separated Values) format.
    </para>
    <tip><title>Tip!</title>
    <para>
      This window will be updated frequently, so it will be useful, even if
      you open it before (or while) you are doing a live capture.
    </para>
    </tip>
    </section>
    <section id="ChStatConversationListWindow">
      <title>The protocol specific "Conversation List" windows</title>
      <para>
    Before the combined window described above was available, each of its
    pages was shown as a separate window. Even though the combined window is
    much more convenient to use, these separate windows are still
    available. The main reason is that they might process faster for
    very large capture files. However, as the functionality is exactly the
    same as in the combined window, they won't be discussed in detail here.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="ChStatEndpoints">
    <title>Endpoints</title>
    <para>
      Statistics of the endpoints captured.
      <tip><title>Tip!</title>
      <para>
    If you are looking for a feature other network tools call a <command>
    hostlist</command>, here is the right place to look. The list of
    Ethernet or IP endpoints is usually what you're looking for.
      </para>
      </tip>
    </para>
    <section id="ChStatEndpointDefinition"><title>What is an Endpoint?</title>
    <para>
      A network endpoint is the logical endpoint of separate protocol traffic of
      a specific protocol layer. The endpoint statistics of Wireshark will take
      the following endpoints into account:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
    <para>
      <command>Ethernet</command>: an Ethernet endpoint is identical to the
      Ethernet's MAC address.
    </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
    <para>
      <command>Fibre Channel</command>: XXX - insert info here.
    </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
    <para>
      <command>FDDI</command>: a FDDI endpoint is identical to the FDDI MAC
      address.
    </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
    <para>
      <command>IPv4</command>: an IP endpoint is identical to its IP address.
    </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
    <para>
      <command>IPX</command>: an IPX endpoint is concatenation of a 32 bit
      network number and 48 bit node address, be default the Ethernets' MAC
      address.
    </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
    <para>
      <command>JXTA</command>: a JXTA endpoint is a 160 bit SHA-1 URN.
    </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
    <para>
      <command>NCP</command>: XXX - insert info here.
    </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
    <para>
      <command>RSVP</command>: XXX - insert info here.
    </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
    <para>
      <command>SCTP</command>: a SCTP endpoint is a combination of the host IP
      addresses (plural) and the SCTP port used. So different SCTP ports on the
      same IP address are different SCTP endpoints, but the same SCTP port on
      different IP addresses of the same host are still the same endpoint.
    </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
    <para>
      <command>TCP</command>: a TCP endpoint is a combination of the IP address
      and the TCP port used, so different TCP ports on the same IP address are
      different TCP endpoints.
    </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
    <para>
      <command>Token Ring</command>: a Token Ring endpoint is identical to the
      Token Ring MAC address.
    </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
    <para>
      <command>UDP</command>: a UDP endpoint is a combination of the IP address
      and the UDP port used, so different UDP ports on the same IP address are
      different UDP endpoints.
    </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
    <para>
      <command>USB</command>: XXX - insert info here.
    </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
    <para>
      <command>WLAN</command>: XXX - insert info here.
    </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <note><title>Broadcast / multicast endpoints</title>
    <para>
      Broadcast / multicast traffic will be shown separately as additional
      endpoints. Of course, as these endpoints are virtual endpoints, the real
      traffic will be received by all (multicast: some) of the listed unicast
      endpoints.
    </para>
    </note>
    </section>
    <section id="ChStatEndpointsWindow">
      <title>The "Endpoints" window</title>
      <para>
    This window shows statistics about the endpoints captured.
      </para>
      <figure><title>The "Endpoints" window</title>
      <graphic entityref="WiresharkStatsEndpoints" format="PNG"/>
      </figure>
      <para>
    For each supported protocol, a tab is shown in this window.
    Each tab label shows the number of endpoints captured (e.g. the
    tab label "Ethernet: 5" tells you that five ethernet endpoints have been
    captured). If no endpoints of a specific protocol were captured, the tab
    label will be greyed out (although the related page can still be selected).
      </para>
      <para>
    Each row in the list shows the statistical values for exactly one endpoint.
      </para>
      <para>
    <command>Name resolution</command> will be done if selected in the window
    and if it is active for the specific protocol layer (MAC layer for the
    selected Ethernet endpoints page). As you might have noticed, the first
    row has a name
    resolution of the first three bytes "Netgear", the second row's address was
    resolved to an IP address (using ARP) and the third was resolved
    to a broadcast (unresolved this would still be: ff:ff:ff:ff:ff:ff); the last two
    Ethernet addresses remain unresolved.
      </para>
      <para>
    <command>Limit to display filter</command> will only show conversations matching
    the current display filter.
      </para>
      <para>
    The <command>copy</command> button will copy the list values to the
    clipboard in CSV (Comma Separated Values) format.
      </para>
      <tip><title>Tip!</title>
      <para>
    This window will be updated frequently, so it will be useful, even if
    you open it before (or while) you are doing a live capture.
      </para>
      </tip>
    </section>
    <section id="ChStatEndpointListWindow">
      <title>The protocol specific "Endpoint List" windows</title>
      <para>
    Before the combined window described above was available, each of its
    pages was shown as a separate window. Even though the combined window is
    much more convenient to use, these separate windows are still
    available. The main reason is that they might process faster for
    very large capture files. However, as the functionality is exactly the
    same as in the combined window, they won't be discussed in detail here.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="ChStatIOGraphs">
    <title>The "IO Graphs" window</title>
    <para>
    User configurable graph of the captured network packets.
    </para>
    <para>
    You can define up to five differently colored graphs.
    </para>

    <figure><title>The "IO Graphs" window</title>
      <graphic entityref="WiresharkStatsIOGraphs" format="PNG"/>
    </figure>

    <para>
    The user can configure the following things:
    <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
    <para><command>Graphs</command>
    <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
    <para>
    <command>Graph 1-5</command>: enable the specific graph 1-5 (only graph 1 is enabled
    by default)
    </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
    <para>
    <command>Color</command>: the color of the graph (cannot be changed)
    </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
    <para>
    <command>Filter</command>: a display filter for this graph (only the
    packets that pass this filter will be taken into account for this graph)
    </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
    <para>
    <command>Style</command>: the style of the graph (Line/Impulse/FBar/Dot)
    </para>
    </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
    <para><command>X Axis</command>
    <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
    <para>
    <command>Tick interval</command>: an interval in x direction lasts
    (10/1 minutes or 10/1/0.1/0.01/0.001 seconds)
    </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
    <para>
    <command>Pixels per tick</command>: use 10/5/2/1 pixels per tick interval
    </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
    <para>
    <command>View as time of day</command>: option to view x direction labels
    as time of day instead of seconds or minutes since beginning of capture
    </para>
    </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
    <para><command>Y Axis</command>
    <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
    <para>
    <command>Unit</command>: the unit for the y direction (Packets/Tick,
    Bytes/Tick, Bits/Tick, Advanced...) [XXX - describe the Advanced feature.]
    </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
    <para>
    <command>Scale</command>: the scale for the y unit
    (Logarithmic,Auto,10,20,50,100,200,500,...)
    </para>
    </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    </listitem>

    </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    <para>
      The <command>save</command> button will save the currently displayed
      portion of the graph as one of various file formats.
    </para>
    <para>
      The <command>copy</command> button will copy values from selected
      graphs to the clipboard in CSV (Comma Separated Values) format.
    </para>
    <tip><title>Tip!</title>
    <para>
      Click in the graph to select the first package in the selected interval.
    </para>
    </tip>
  </section>

  <section id="ChStatSRT">
    <title>Service Response Time</title>
    <para>
    The service response time is the time between a request and the
    corresponding response. This information is available for many protocols.
    </para>
    <para>
    Service response time statistics are currently available for the following
    protocols:
    <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
    <para><command>DCE-RPC</command></para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
    <para><command>Fibre Channel</command></para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
    <para><command>H.225 RAS</command></para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
    <para><command>LDAP</command></para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
    <para><command>LTE MAC</command></para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
    <para><command>MGCP</command></para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
    <para><command>ONC-RPC</command></para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
    <para><command>SMB</command></para>
    </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    As an example, the DCE-RPC service response time is described in more
    detail.
    <note><title>Note!</title>
    <para>
    The other Service Response Time windows will work the same way (or only
    slightly different) compared to the following description.
    </para>
    </note>
    </para>
  <section id="ChStatSRTDceRpc">
    <title>The "Service Response Time DCE-RPC" window</title>
    <para>
    The service response time of DCE-RPC is the time between the request and
    the corresponding response.
    </para>
    <para>
    First of all, you have to select the DCE-RPC interface:
    </para>
    <figure><title>The "Compute DCE-RPC statistics" window</title>
      <graphic entityref="WiresharkStatsSrtDcerpcFilter" format="PNG"/>
    </figure>
    <para>
    You can optionally set a display filter, to reduce the amount of packets.
    </para>
    <figure><title>The "DCE-RPC Statistic for ..." window</title>
      <graphic entityref="WiresharkStatsSrtDcerpc" format="PNG"/>
    </figure>
    <para>
    Each row corresponds to a method of the interface selected (so the EPM
    interface in version 3 has 7 methods). For each
    method the number of calls, and the statistics of the SRT time is
    calculated.
    </para>
  </section>
  </section>
  <section id="ChStatCompareCaptureFiles">
    <title>Compare two capture files</title>
    <para>
      Compare two capture files.
    </para>

    <para>
      This feature works best when you have merged two capture files
      chronologically, one from each side of a client/server connection.
    </para>

    <para>
      The merged capture data is checked for missing packets. If a matching
      connection is found it is checked for:
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
            <para>
             IP header checksums
            </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
            <para>
             Excessive delay (defined by the "Time variance" setting)
            </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
            <para>
             Packet order
            </para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </para>

    <figure><title>The "Compare" window</title>
     <graphic entityref="WiresharkStatsCompare" format="PNG"/>
    </figure>

    <para>
        You can configure the following:
        <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
        <para>
            <command>Start compare:</command> Start comparing when this many
            IP IDs are matched. A zero value starts comparing immediately.
        </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
        <para>
            <command>Stop compare:</command> Stop comparing when we can no longer
            match this many IP IDs. Zero always compares.
        </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
        <para>
            <command>Endpoint distinction:</command> Use MAC addresses or IP
            time-to-live values to determine connection endpoints.
        </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
        <para>
            <command>Check order:</command> Check for the same IP ID in the
            previous packet at each end.
        </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
        <para>
            <command>Time variance:</command> Trigger an error if the packet
            arrives this many milliseconds after the average delay.
        </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
        <para>
            <command>Filter:</command> Limit comparison to packets that match
            this display filter.
        </para>
        </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </para>

    <para>
        The info column contains new numbering so the same packets are parallel.
    </para>
    <para>
        The color filtering differentiate the two files from each other. A
        “zebra” effect is create if the Info column is sorted.
    </para>

    <tip><title>Tip!</title>
    <para>
        If you click on an item in the error list its corresponding packet will
        be selected in the main window.
    </para>
    </tip>


  </section>
  <section id="ChStatWLANTraffic">
    <title>WLAN Traffic Statistics</title>
    <para>
      Statistics of the captured WLAN traffic.  This window will summarize the
      wireless network traffic found in the capture.  Probe requests will be
      merged into an existing network if the SSID matches.
    </para>

    <figure><title>The "WLAN Traffic Statistics" window</title>
    <graphic entityref="WiresharkStatsWLANTraffic" format="PNG"/>
    </figure>

    <para>
      Each row in the list shows the statistical values for exactly one wireless network.
    </para>
    <para>
      <command>Name resolution</command> will be done if selected in the window
      and if it is active for the MAC layer.
    </para>
    <para>
      <command>Only show existing networks</command> will exclude probe requests
      with a SSID not matching any network from the list.
    </para>
    <para>
      The <command>copy</command> button will copy the list values to the
      clipboard in CSV (Comma Separated Values) format.
    </para>
    <tip><title>Tip!</title>
    <para>
      This window will be updated frequently, so it will be useful, even if
      you open it before (or while) you are doing a live capture.
    </para>
    </tip>
  </section>
 
  <section id="ChStatXXX">
    <title>The protocol specific statistics windows</title>
    <para>
    The protocol specific statistics windows display detailed information
    of specific protocols and might be described in a later
    version of this document.
    </para>
    <para>
    Some of these statistics are described at the
    <ulink url="&WiresharkWikiPage;/Statistics"/> pages.
    </para>
  </section>

</chapter>
<!-- End of WSUG Chapter Statistics -->

