<!-- WSUG Appendix Messages -->
<!-- $Id$ -->

<appendix id="AppMessages">
  <title>Ethereal Messages</title>
  <para>
  Ethereal provides you with additional information generated out of 
  the plain packet data or it may need to indicate dissection problems.
  Messages generated by Wireshark are usually placed in [] parentheses.
  </para>
  <section id="AppMessagesList"><title>Packet List Messages</title>
    <para>
	These messages might appear in the packet list.
    </para>
  <section><title>[Malformed Packet]</title>
    <para>
	Malformed packet means that the protocol dissector can't work out the 
	contents of the packet any further. This can have various reasons:
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
		<command>Wrong dissector</command>
	    Ethereal errorneously has chosen the wrong protocol dissector for 
		this packet. This will happen e.g. if you are using a protocol  
		not on it's well known TCP or UDP port. You may try Analyze|Decode As 
		to circumvent this problem.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
		<command>Packet not reassembled</command>
		The packet is longer than a single frame and it is not reassembled,
		see	<xref linkend="ChAdvReassemblySection"/> for further details.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
		<command>Packet is malformed</command>
	    The packet is actually wrong (malformed), meaning that a part of the 
		packet is just not as expected (not following the protocol 
		specifications).
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
		<command>Dissector is buggy</command>
	    The corresponding protocol dissector is simply buggy or still
		incomplete.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    <para>
	Any of the above is possible. You'll have to look into the specific 
	situation to determine what it is. 
	You could disable the dissector by disabling the
	protocol on the Analyze menu and check how Ethereal displays the packet
	then. You could (if it's TCP) enable reassembly for TCP and the specific
	dissector (if possible) in the Edit|Preferences menu. You could check the
	packet contents yourself by reading the packet bytes and comparing it to
	the protocol specification. This could reveil a dissector bug. Or you
	could find out that the packet is indeed wrong.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section><title>[Packet size limited during capture]</title>
    <para>
	The packet size was limited during capture, see "Limit each packet to n 
	bytes" at the <xref linkend="ChCapCaptureOptions"/>. 
	While dissecting, the current protocol 
	dissector was simply running out of packet bytes and had to give up.
	There's nothing else you can do now, except to repeat the whole capture 
	process again with a higher (or no) packet size limitation.
    </para>
  </section>
  </section>

  <section id="AppMessagesDetails"><title>Packet Details Messages</title>
    <para>
	These messages might appear in the packet details.
    </para>
  <section><title>[Response in frame: 123]</title>
    <para>
	The current packet is the request of a detected request/response pair. 
	You can directly jump to the corresponding response packet just 
	by double clicking on this message.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section><title>[Request in frame: 123]</title>
    <para>
	Same as "Response in frame: 123" above, but the other way round.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section><title>[Time from request: 0.123 seconds]</title>
    <para>
	The time between the request and the response packets.
    </para>
  </section>
  </section>

</appendix>
<!-- End of WSUG Appendix Messages -->
