<!-- WSUG Chapter Telephony -->

<chapter id="ChTelephony">
  <title>Telephony</title>
  <section id="ChTelIntroduction">
  <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>
    Wireshark provides a wide range of telephony related network statistics
    which can be accessed via the <command>Telephony</command> menu.
    </para>
    <para>
    These statistics range from specific signaling protocols, to analysis of
    signaling and media flows. If encoded in a compatible encoding the media
    flow can even be played.
    </para>
  </section>
  
  <section id="ChTelRTPAnalysis">
    <title>RTP Analysis</title>
    <para>
    The RTP analysis function takes the selected RTP stream (and the reverse
    stream, if possible) and generates a list of statistics on it.
    </para>
    <figure><title>The "RTP Stream Analysis" window</title>
    <graphic entityref="WiresharkTelRTPStreamAnalysis" format="PNG"/>
    </figure>
    <para>
    Starting with basic data as packet number and sequence number, further
    statistics are created based on arrival time, delay, jitter, packet size,
    etc.
    </para>
    <para>
    Besides the per packet statistics, the lower pane shows the overall
    statistics, with minimums and maximums for delta, jitter and clock skew.
    Also an indication of lost packets is included.
    </para>
    <para>
    The RTP Stream Analysis window further provides the option to save the RTP
    payload (as raw data or, if in a PCM encoding, in an Audio file). Other
    options a to export and plot various statistics on the RTP streams.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="ChTelVoipCalls">
    <title>VoIP Calls</title>
    <para>
    The VoIP Calls window shows a list of all detected VoIP calls in the
    captured traffic. It finds calls by their signaling.
    </para>
    <para>
    More details are described at the
    <ulink url="&WiresharkWikiPage;/VoIP_calls"/> page.
    </para>
  </section>
  
  <section id="ChTelLTEMACTraffic">
    <title>LTE MAC Traffic Statistics</title>
    <para>
      Statistics of the captured LTE MAC traffic.  This window will summarize the
      LTE MAC traffic found in the capture.
    </para>

    <figure><title>The "LTE MAC Traffic Statistics" window</title>
    <graphic entityref="WiresharkStatsLTEMACTraffic" format="PNG"/>
    </figure>

    <para>
      The top pane shows statistics for common channels.
      Each row in the middle pane shows statistical highlights for exactly one UE/C-RNTI.
      In the lower pane, you can see the for the currently selected UE/C-RNTI
      the traffic broken down by individual channel.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="ChTelLTERLCTraffic">
    <title>LTE RLC Traffic Statistics</title>
    <para>
      Statistics of the captured LTE RLC traffic.  This window will summarize the
      LTE RLC traffic found in the capture.
    </para>

    <figure><title>The "LTE RLC Traffic Statistics" window</title>
    <graphic entityref="WiresharkStatsLTERLCTraffic" format="PNG"/>
    </figure>

    <para>
      At the top, the check-box allows this window to include RLC PDUs found
      within MAC PDUs or not.  This will affect both the PDUs counted as well
      as the display filters generated (see below).
    </para>

    <para>
      The upper list shows summaries of each active UE.
      Each row in the lower list shows statistical highlights for individual
      channels within the selected UE.
    </para>

    <para>
      The lower part of the windows allows display filters to be generated and
      set for the selected channel.  Note that in the case of Acknowledged
      Mode channels, if a single direction is chosen, the generated filter will
      show data in that direction and control PDUs in the opposite direction.
    </para>

  </section>


  <section id="ChTelXXX">
    <title>The protocol specific statistics windows</title>
    <para>
    The protocol specific statistics windows display detailed information
    of specific protocols and might be described in a later
    version of this document.
    </para>
    <para>
    Some of these statistics are described at the
    <ulink url="&WiresharkWikiPage;/Statistics"/> pages.
    </para>
  </section>

</chapter>
<!-- End of WSUG Chapter Telephony -->

