<!-- WSUG Chapter Capture -->
<!-- $Id$ -->

<chapter id="ChapterCapture">
  <title>Capturing Live Network Data</title>
  
  <section id="ChCapIntroduction">
	<title>Introduction</title>
	<para>
	Capturing live network data is one of the major features of Wireshark.
	</para>
	<para>
	The Wireshark capture engine provides the following features:
	</para>
	<para>
	<itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>
	Capture from different kinds of network hardware (Ethernet, Token Ring, 
	ATM, ...).
	</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>
	Stop the capture on different triggers like: amount of captured data, 
	captured time, captured number of packets.
	</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>
	Simultaneously show decoded packets while keep on capturing.
	</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>
	Filter packets, reducing the amount of data to be captured, see <xref 
	linkend="ChCapCaptureFilterSection"/>.
	</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>
	Capturing into multiple files while doing a long term capture, and in 
	addition the option to form a ringbuffer of these files, keeping only 
	the last x files, useful for a "very long term" capture, see <xref 
	linkend="ChCapCaptureFiles"/>.
	</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	The capture engine still lacks the following features:
	<itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>
	Simultaneous capturing from multiple network interfaces (however, you 
	can start multiple instances of Wireshark and merge capture files later).
	</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>
	Stop capturing (or doing some other action), depending on the captured 
	data.
	</para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	</para>
  </section>

  <section id="ChCapPrerequisitesSection"><title>Prerequisites</title>
    <para>
	Setting up Wireshark to capture packets for the first time can be tricky. 
	</para>
	<tip><title>Tip!</title><para>
	A comprehensive guide "How To setup a Capture" is available at:
	<ulink url="&WiresharkWikiPage;/CaptureSetup">&WiresharkWikiPage;/CaptureSetup</ulink>.
	</para></tip>
	<para>
	Here are some common pitfalls:
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
		You need to have root / Administrator privileges to start a live 
		capture.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
		You need to choose the right network interface to capture packet data 
		from.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
		You need to capture at the right place in the network to see the 
		traffic you want to see.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
		... and a lot more!.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
	</para>
	<para>
	If you have any problems setting up your capture environment, you should 
	have a look at the guide mentioned above.
	</para>
  </section>

  <section id="ChCapCapturingSection"><title>Start Capturing</title>
    <para>
      One of the following methods can be used to start capturing packets with 
	  Wireshark:
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    You can get an overview of the available local interfaces using the 
		"<inlinegraphic entityref="WiresharkToolbarCaptureInterfaces" format="PNG"/>
		Capture Interfaces" dialog box, see 
		<xref linkend="ChCapCaptureInterfacesDialog"/>. You can start a 
		capture from this dialog box, using (one of) the "Capture" button(s).
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    You can start capturing using the 
		"<inlinegraphic entityref="WiresharkToolbarCaptureOptions" format="PNG"/>
		Capture Options" dialog box, see 
		<xref linkend="ChCapCaptureOptionsDialog"/>.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    If you have selected the right capture options before, you can 
		immediately start a capture using the 
		"<inlinegraphic entityref="WiresharkToolbarCaptureStart" format="PNG"/>
		Capture Start" menu / toolbar item. The capture
		process will start immediately.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    If you already know the name of the capture interface, you can start 
		Wireshark from the command line and use the following:
	    <programlisting>
wireshark -i eth0 -k
	    </programlisting>
		This will start Wireshark capturing on interface eth0, more details 
		can be found at: <xref linkend="ChCustCommandLine"/>.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    </section>

  <section id="ChCapInterfaceSection">
	<title>The "Capture Interfaces" dialog box</title>
	<para>
	When you select "Interfaces..." from the Capture menu, Wireshark pops 
	up the "Capture Interfaces" dialog box as shown in 
	<xref linkend="ChCapCaptureInterfacesDialog"/>.
	<warning><title>Warning!</title>
	<para>
	As the "Capture Interfaces" dialog is showing live captured data, it is 
	consuming a lot of system ressources. Close this dialog as soon as 
	possible to prevent excessive system load.
	</para>
	</warning>
	<note><title>Note!</title>
	<para>
	This dialog box will only show the local interfaces Wireshark knows 
	of. As Wireshark might not be able to detect all local interfaces, and it 
	cannot detect the remote interfaces available, there could be more capture 
	interfaces available than listed.
	</para>
	</note>
	<figure id="ChCapCaptureInterfacesDialog">
	<title>The "Capture Interfaces" dialog box</title>
	<graphic entityref="WiresharkCaptureInterfacesDialog" format="PNG"/>
	</figure>
	<variablelist>
	  <varlistentry><term><command>Description</command></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		  The interface description provided by the operating system.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry><term><command>IP</command></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		  The first IP address Wireshark could resolve from this interface. 
		  If no address could be resolved (e.g. no DHCP server available), 
		  "unknown" will be displayed. If more than one IP address could be 
		  resolved, only the first is shown (unpredictable which one in that 
		  case).
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry><term><command>Packets</command></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		  The number of packets captured from this interface, since this 
		  dialog was opened. Will be greyed out, if no packet was captured 
		  in the last second.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry><term><command>Packets/s</command></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		  Number of packets captured in the last second. Will be greyed out, 
		  if no packet was captured in the last second.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry><term><command>Stop</command></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		  Stop a currently running capture.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry><term><command>Capture</command></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		  Start a capture on this interface immediately, using the settings 
		  from the last capture.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry><term><command>Options</command></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		  Open the Capture Options dialog with this interface selected, see 
		  <xref linkend="ChCapCaptureOptions"/>.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry><term><command>Details (Win32 only)</command></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		  Open a dialog with detailed information about the interface.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry><term><command>Close</command></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		  Close this dialog box.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	</variablelist>
	</para>
  </section>
  
    <section id="ChCapCaptureOptions">
      <title>The "Capture Options" dialog box</title>
      <para>
	When you select Start... from the Capture menu (or use the corresponding 
	item in the "Main" toolbar), Wireshark pops 
	up the "Capture Options" dialog box as shown in 
	<xref linkend="ChCapCaptureOptionsDialog"/>.
      </para>
      <figure id="ChCapCaptureOptionsDialog">
	<title>The "Capture Options" dialog box</title>
	<graphic entityref="WiresharkCaptureOptionsDialog" format="JPG"/>
      </figure>
	<tip><title>Tip!</title>
	<para>
	If you are unsure which options to choose in this dialog box, just try 
	keeping the defaults as this should work well in many cases.
	</para>
	</tip>
	<para>
	You can set the following fields in this dialog box:
	</para>
	<section><title>Capture frame</title>
	<variablelist>
	  <varlistentry><term><command>Interface</command></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		This field specifies the interface you want to capture on. 
		You can only capture on one interface, and you can only 
		capture on interfaces that Wireshark has found on the 
		system. It is a drop-down list, so simply click on the 
		button on the right hand side and select the interface you 
		want. It defaults to the first non-loopback interface that 
		supports capturing, and if there are none, the first 
		loopback interface. On some systems, loopback interfaces 
		cannot be used for capturing (loopback interfaces are not available 
		on Windows platforms).
	      </para>
	      <para>
		This field performs the same function as the 
		<command>-i &lt;interface></command> command line option.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry><term><command>IP address</command></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		  The IP address(es) of the selected interface. If no address could 
		  be resolved from the system, "unknown" will be shown.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry><term><command>Link-layer header type</command></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		  Unless you are in the rare situation that you need this, just keep 
		  the default. For a detailed description, see 
		  <xref linkend="ChCapLinkLayerHeader"/>
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry><term><command>Buffer size: n megabyte(s)</command></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		  Enter the buffer size to be used while capturing. This is the size 
		  of the kernel buffer which will keep the captured packets, until 
		  they are written to disk. If you encounter packet drops, try 
		  increasing this value.
	      </para>
	      <note>
		  <title>Note</title>
		  <para>This option is only available on Windows platforms.</para>
	      </note>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry>
	    <term>
	      <command>Capture packets in promiscuous mode</command>
	    </term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		This checkbox allows you to specify that Wireshark 
		should put the interface in promiscuous mode when capturing. 
		If you do not specify this, Wireshark will only capture the 
		packets going to or from your computer (not 
		all packets on your LAN segment).
	      </para>
	      <note>
		<title>Note</title>
		<para>
		  If some other process has put the interface in 
		  promiscuous mode you may be capturing in promiscuous 
		  mode even if you turn off this option
		</para>
	      </note>
	      <note>
		<title>Note</title>
		<para>
		Even in promiscuous mode you still won't necessarily see all packets 
		on your LAN segment, see <ulink url="&WiresharkFAQPromiscPage;"/> for 
		some more explanations.
		</para>
	      </note>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry><term><command>Limit each packet to n bytes</command></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		This field allows you to specify the maximum amount of 
		data that will be captured for each packet, and is 
		sometimes referred to as the <command>snaplen</command>. If disabled, 
		the default is 65535, which will be sufficient for most 
		protocols. Some rules of thumb:
	      </para>
		<itemizedlist>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
			If you are unsure, just keep the default value.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
			If you don't need all of the data in a packet - for example, if you
			only need the link-layer, IP, and TCP headers - you might want to
			choose a small snapshot length, as less CPU time is required for
			copying packets, less buffer space is required for packets, and thus
			perhaps fewer packets will be dropped if traffic is very heavy.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
			If you don't capture all of the data in a packet, you might find that
			the packet data you want is in the part that's dropped, or that
			reassembly isn't possible as the data required for reassembly is
			missing.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry><term><command>Capture Filter</command></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		This field allows you to specify a capture filter. 
		Capture filters are discussed in more details in 
		<xref linkend="ChCapCaptureFilterSection"/>. It defaults to empty, or 
		  no filter.
	      </para>
	      <para>
		You can also click on the button labelled Capture Filter, and Wireshark 
		will bring up the Capture Filters dialog box and allow you to create 
		and/or select a filter.  Please see 
		<xref linkend="ChWorkDefineFilterSection"/>
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	</variablelist>
	</section>
	<section><title>Capture File(s) frame</title>
	<para>
	An explanation about capture file usage can be found in <xref 
	linkend="ChCapCaptureFiles"/>.
	</para>
	<variablelist>	  
	  <varlistentry><term><command>File</command></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
			This field allows you to specify the file name that will be 
			used for the capture file. This field is left blank by default.
			If the field is left blank, the capture data will be stored in a 
			temporary file, see <xref linkend="ChCapCaptureFiles"/> for 
			details.
	      </para>
	      <para>
			You can also click on the button to the right of this field to 
			browse through the filesystem.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry><term><command>Use multiple files</command></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
			Instead of using a single file, Wireshark will automatically switch 
			to a new one, if a specific trigger condition is reached.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry><term><command>Next file every n megabyte(s)</command></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
			Multiple files only: Switch to the next file after the given 
			number of byte(s)/kilobyte(s)/megabyte(s)/gigabyte(s) have been
			captured. 
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry><term><command>Next file every n minute(s)</command></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
			Multiple files only: Switch to the next file after the given 
			number of second(s)/minutes(s)/hours(s)/days(s) have elapsed.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry><term><command>Ring buffer with n files</command></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
			Multiple files only: Form a ring buffer of the capture files, with 
			the given number of files.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry><term><command>Stop capture after n file(s)</command></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
			Multiple files only: Stop capturing after switching to the next 
			file the given number of times.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	</variablelist>
	</section>
	<section><title>Stop Capture... frame</title>
	<variablelist>	  
	  <varlistentry><term><command>... after n packet(s)</command></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
			Stop capturing after the given number of packets have been
			captured.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry><term><command>... after n megabytes(s)</command></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
			Stop capturing after the given number of 
			byte(s)/kilobyte(s)/megabyte(s)/gigabyte(s) have been captured.
			This option is greyed out, if "Use multiple files" is selected.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry><term><command>... after n minute(s)</command></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
			Stop capturing after the given number of 
			second(s)/minutes(s)/hours(s)/days(s) have elapsed.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	</variablelist>
	</section>
	<section><title>Display Options frame</title>
	<variablelist>	  
	  <varlistentry>
	    <term>
	      <command>Update list of packets in real time</command>
	    </term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		This option allows you to specify that Wireshark 
		should update the packet list pane in real time. If you 
		do not specify this, Wireshark does not display any 
		packets until you stop the capture. When you check this,
		Wireshark captures in a separate process 
		and feeds the captures to the display process.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry>
	    <term>
	      <command>Automatic scrolling in live capture</command>
	    </term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		This option allows you to specify that Wireshark 
		should scroll the packet list pane as new packets come 
		in, so you are always looking at the last packet.  If you 
		do not specify this, Wireshark simply adds new packets onto 
		the end of the list, but does not scroll the packet list 
		pane. This option is greyed out if 
		"Update list of packets in real time" is disabled.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry>
	    <term>
	      <command>Hide capture info dialog</command>
	    </term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		If this option is checked, the following capture info dialog will be 
		hidden.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	</variablelist>
	</section>
	<section><title>Name Resolution frame</title>
	<variablelist>	  
	  <varlistentry>
	    <term><command>Enable MAC name resolution</command></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		This option allows you to control whether or not 
		Wireshark translates MAC addresses into names, see 
		<xref linkend="ChAdvNameResolutionSection"/>.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry>
	    <term><command>Enable network name resolution</command></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		This option allows you to control whether or not 
		Wireshark translates network addresses into names, see
		<xref linkend="ChAdvNameResolutionSection"/>.
	      </para>  
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry>
	    <term><command>Enable transport name resolution</command></term>
	    <listitem>
	      <para>
		This option allows you to control whether or not 
		Wireshark translates transport addresses into protocols, see
		<xref linkend="ChAdvNameResolutionSection"/>.
	      </para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	</variablelist>
	</section>
	<section><title>Buttons</title>
      <para>
	Once you have set the values you desire and have selected the 
	options you need, simply click on <command>Start</command> to commence the 
	capture, or <command>Cancel</command> to cancel the capture.
      </para>
      <para>
	If you start a capture, Wireshark allows you to stop capturing when 
	you have enough packets captured, for details see
		<xref linkend="ChCapRunningSection"/>.
      </para>
    </section>
    </section>
	
    <section id="ChCapCaptureFiles"><title>Capture files and file modes</title>
	<para>
	While capturing, the underlying libpcap capturing engine will grab the 
	packets from the network card and keep the packet data in a (relatively) 
	small kernel buffer. This data is read by Wireshark and saved into 
	the capture file(s) the user specified.
	</para>

	<para>
	Different modes of operation are available when saving this packet data to 
	the capture file(s).
	</para>
	
	<tip><title>Tip!</title>
	<para>
	Working with large files (several 100 MB's) can be quite slow. If you plan 
	to do a long term capture or capturing from a high traffic network, think 
	about using one of the "Multiple files" options. This  will spread the 
	captured packets over several smaller files which can be much more 
	pleasant to work with.
	</para>
	</tip>
	<note><title>Note!</title>
	<para>
	Using Multiple files may cut context related information.
	Wireshark keeps context information of the loaded packet data, so it can 
	report context related problems (like a stream error) and keeps information
	about context related protocols (e.g. where data is exchanged at the 
	establishing phase and only referred to in later packets). 
	As it keeps this information only for the loaded file, using one of 
	the multiple file modes may cut these contexts. If the establishing phase 
	is saved in one file and the things you would like to see is in another, 
	you might not see some of the valuable context related information.
	</para>
	</note>
	<tip><title>Tip!</title>
	<para>
	Information about the folders used for the capture file(s), can be found 
	in <xref linkend="AppFiles"/>. 
	</para>
	</tip>
	
    <table id="ChCapTabCaptureFiles"><title>Capture file mode selected by capture options</title>
      <tgroup cols="5">
	<colspec colnum="1" colwidth="72pt"/>
	  <colspec colnum="2" colwidth="80pt"/>
	  <colspec colnum="3" colwidth="80pt"/>
	  <colspec colnum="4" colwidth="80pt"/>
	    <thead>
	      <row>
		<entry>"File" option</entry>
		<entry>"Use multiple files" option</entry>
		<entry>"Ring buffer with n files" option</entry>
		<entry>Mode</entry>
		<entry>Resulting filename(s) used</entry>
	      </row>
	    </thead>
	    <tbody>
	      <row>
		<entry>-</entry>
		<entry>-</entry>
		<entry>-</entry>
		<entry><command>Single temporary file</command></entry>
		<entry>etherXXXXXX (where XXXXXX is a unique number)</entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>foo.cap</entry>
		<entry>-</entry>
		<entry>-</entry>
		<entry><command>Single named file</command></entry>
		<entry>foo.cap</entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>foo.cap</entry>
		<entry>x</entry>
		<entry>-</entry>
		<entry><command>Multiple files, continuous</command></entry>
		<entry>foo_00001_20040205110102.cap, foo_00002_20040205110102.cap, ...</entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>foo.cap</entry>
		<entry>x</entry>
		<entry>x</entry>
		<entry><command>Multiple files, ring buffer</command></entry>
		<entry>foo_00001_20040205110102.cap, foo_00002_20040205110102.cap, ...</entry>
	      </row>
	    </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
	<variablelist>
	  <varlistentry>
	    <term><command>Single temporary file</command></term>
	    <listitem>
	<para>
	A temporary file will be created and used (this is the default). After the 
	capturing is stopped, this file can be saved later under a user specified 
	name.
	</para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry>
	    <term><command>Single named file</command></term>
	    <listitem>
	<para>
	A single capture file will be used. If you want to place the new capture 
	file to a specific folder, choose this mode.
	</para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry>
	    <term><command>Multiple files, continuous</command></term>
	    <listitem>
	<para>
	Like the "Single named file" mode, but a new file is created and used, 
	after reaching one of the multiple file switch conditions (one of the 
	"Next file every ..." values).
	</para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	  <varlistentry>
	    <term><command>Multiple files, ring buffer</command></term>
	    <listitem>
	<para>
	Much like "Multiple files continuous", reaching one of the multiple files 
	switch conditions (one of the "Next file every ..." values) will switch 
	to the next file. This will be a newly created file if value of "Ring 
	buffer with n files" is not reached, otherwise it will replace the oldest 
	of the formerly used files (thus forming a "ring").
	</para>
	<para>
	This mode will limit the maximum disk usage, even for an unlimited amount of 
	capture input data, keeping the latest captured data.
	</para>
	    </listitem>
	  </varlistentry>
	</variablelist>
	</section>

  <section id="ChCapLinkLayerHeader"><title>Link-layer header type</title>
	<para>
	In the usual case, you won't have to choose this link-layer header type. 
	The following paragraphs describe the exceptional cases, where
	selecting this type is possible, so you will have a guide of what to do:
	</para>
    <para>
    If you are capturing on an 802.11 device on some versions of BSD, this 
	might offer a choice of "Ethernet" or "802.11".  "Ethernet" will cause 
	the captured packets to have fake Ethernet headers; "802.11" will cause 
	them to have IEEE 802.11 headers.  Unless the capture needs to be read by 
	an application that doesn't support 802.11 headers, you should select 
	"802.11".
	</para>
	<para>
    If you are capturing on an Endace DAG card connected to a synchronous 
	serial line, this might offer a choice of "PPP over serial" or 
	"Cisco HDLC"; if the protocol on the serial line is PPP, select 
	"PPP over serial", and if the protocol on the serial line is Cisco HDLC, 
	select "Cisco HDLC".
	</para>
	<para>
    If you are capturing on an Endace DAG card connected to an ATM network, 
	this might offer a choice of "RFC 1483 IP-over-ATM" or "Sun raw ATM".  
	If the only traffic being captured is RFC 1483 LLC-encapsulated IP, or if 
	the capture needs to be read by an application that doesn't support SunATM 
	headers, select "RFC 1483 IP-over-ATM", otherwise select "Sun raw ATM".
	</para>
	<para>
    If you are capturing on an Ethernet device, this might offer a choice of 
	"Ethernet" or "DOCSIS".  If you are capturing traffic from a Cisco Cable 
	Modem Termination System that is putting DOCSIS traffic onto the Ethernet 
	to be captured, select "DOCSIS", otherwise select "Ethernet".
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="ChCapCaptureFilterSection"><title>Filtering while capturing</title>
    <para>
      Wireshark uses the libpcap filter language for capture filters. 
      This is explained in the tcpdump man page, which can be hard to 
	  understand, so it's explained here to some extent.
    </para>
    <tip>
      <title>Tip!</title>
      <para>
	  You will find a lot of Capture Filter examples at <ulink 
	  url="&WiresharkWikiCaptureFiltersPage;">&WiresharkWikiCaptureFiltersPage;</ulink>.
      </para>
    </tip>
    <para>
      You enter the capture filter into the Filter field of the Wireshark 
      Capture Options dialog box, as shown in 
      <xref linkend="ChCapCaptureOptionsDialog"/>. The following is an outline 
	  of the syntax of the <command>tcpdump</command> capture filter language. 
	  See the expression option at the tcpdump manual page for details:
	  <ulink url="&TcpdumpManpage;"/>.
    </para>
    <para>
      A capture filter takes the form of a series of primitive expressions 
      connected by conjunctions (<command>and/or</command>) and optionally 
      preceded by <command>not</command>:
      <programlisting>
[not] <command>primitive</command> [and|or [not] <command>primitive</command> ...]
      </programlisting>
      An example is shown in <xref linkend="ChCapExFilt1"/>.

      <example id="ChCapExFilt1">
	<title>
	  A capture filter for telnet that captures traffic to and from a 
	  particular host
	</title>
	<programlisting>
tcp port 23 and host 10.0.0.5
	</programlisting>
      </example>
      This example captures telnet traffic to and from the host 
      10.0.0.5, and shows how to use two primitives and the 
      <command>and</command> conjunction.  Another example is shown in 
      <xref linkend="ChCapExFilt2"/>, and shows how to capture all 
	telnet traffic except that from 10.0.0.5.
	<example id="ChCapExFilt2">
	  <title>
	    Capturing all telnet traffic not from 10.0.0.5</title>
	  <programlisting>
tcp port 23 and not host 10.0.0.5
	  </programlisting>
	</example>
      </para>

      <para>
	  XXX - add examples to the following list.
      </para>
      <para>
      A primitive is simply one of the following:
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><command>[src|dst] host &lt;host></command></term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      This primitive allows you to filter on a host IP 
	      address or name. You can optionally precede the 
	      primitive with the keyword <command>src|dst</command> 
	      to specify that you are only interested in source or 
	      destination addresses. If these are not present, 
	      packets where the specified address appears as either 
	      the source or the destination address will be selected.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <command>ether [src|dst] host &lt;ehost></command>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      This primitive allows you to filter on Ethernet host 
	      addresses. You can optionally include the keyword 
	      <command>src|dst</command> between the keywords 
	      <command>ether</command> and <command>host</command> 
	      to specify that you are only interested in source 
	      or destination addresses.  If these are not present, 
	      packets where the specified address appears in either 
	      the source or destination address will be selected.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><command>gateway host &lt;host></command></term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      This primitive allows you to filter on packets that 
	      used <command>host</command> as a gateway. That is, where 
	      the Ethernet source or destination was 
	      <command>host</command> but neither the source nor 
	      destination IP address was <command>host</command>.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <command>
	      [src|dst] net &lt;net> [{mask &lt;mask>}|{len &lt;len>}]
	    </command>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      This primitive allows you to filter on network numbers. 
	      You can optionally precede this primitive with the 
	      keyword <command>src|dst</command> to specify that you 
	      are only interested in a source or destination network. 
	      If neither of these are present, packets will be 
	      selected that have the specified network in either the
	      source or destination address.  In addition, you can 
	      specify either the netmask or the CIDR prefix for the 
	      network if they are different from your own. 
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>
	    <command>[tcp|udp] [src|dst] port &lt;port></command>
	  </term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      This primitive allows you to filter on TCP and UDP port 
	      numbers. You can optionally precede this primitive with 
	      the keywords <command>src|dst</command> and 
	      <command>tcp|udp</command> which allow you to specify 
	      that you are only interested in source or destination 
	      ports and TCP or UDP packets respectively.  The 
	      keywords <command>tcp|udp</command> must appear before 
	      <command>src|dst</command>.
	    </para>
	    <para>
	      If these are not specified, packets will be selected 
	      for both the TCP and UDP protocols and when the 
	      specified address appears in either the source or 
	      destination port field.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><command>less|greater &lt;length></command></term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      This primitive allows you to filter on packets whose 
	      length was less than or equal to the specified length, 
	      or greater than or equal to the specified length, 
	      respectively.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><command>ip|ether proto &lt;protocol></command></term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      This primitive allows you to filter on the specified 
	      protocol at either the Ethernet layer or the IP layer.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><command>ether|ip broadcast|multicast</command></term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      This primitive allows you to filter on either 
	      Ethernet or IP broadcasts or multicasts.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><command>&lt;expr> relop &lt;expr></command></term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      This primitive allows you to create complex filter 
	      expressions that select bytes or ranges of bytes in 
	      packets.  Please see the tcpdump man page at
		  <ulink url="&TcpdumpManpage;"/> for more details.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
  <section id="ChCapCaptureAutoFilterSection">
    <title>Automatic Remote Traffic Filtering</title>
    <para>
	If Wireshark is running remotely (using e.g. SSH, an exported X11 window, 
	a terminal server, ...), the remote content has to be transported over 
	the network, adding a lot of (usually unimportant) packets to the actually 
	interesting traffic.
    </para>
    <para>	
	To avoid this, Wireshark tries to figure out if it's remotely connected 
	(by looking at some specific environment variables) and automatically 
	creates a capture filter that matches aspects of the connection.  
    </para>
    <para>		
	The following environment variables are analyzed:
    </para>
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><command>SSH_CONNECTION</command> (ssh)</term>
	  <listitem>
    <para>	
   	&lt;remote IP> &lt;remote port> &lt;local IP> &lt;local port>
    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><command>SSH_CLIENT</command> (ssh)</term>
	  <listitem>
    <para>	
   	&lt;remote IP> &lt;remote port> &lt;local port>
    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><command>REMOTEHOST</command> (tcsh, others?)</term>
	  <listitem>
    <para>	
   	&lt;remote name>
    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><command>DISPLAY</command> (x11)</term>
	  <listitem>
    <para>	
   	[remote name]:&lt;display num>
    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term><command>CLIENTNAME</command> (terminal server)</term>
	  <listitem>
    <para>	
   	&lt;remote name>
    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
  </section>
  </section>

  <section id="ChCapRunningSection"><title>While a Capture is running ...</title>
    <para>
	While a capture is running, the following dialog box is shown:
      <figure id="ChCapCaptureInfoDialog">
	<title>The "Capture Info" dialog box</title>
	<graphic entityref="WiresharkCaptureInfoDialog" format="JPG"/>
      </figure>
	This dialog box will inform you about the number of captured packets and 
	the time since the capture was started. The selection of which protocols
	are counted cannot be changed.
	</para>
	  <tip><title>Tip!</title>
	  <para>
	  This Capture Info dialog box can be hidden, using the "Hide capture info 
	  dialog" option in the Capture Options dialog box.
	  </para>
	  </tip>
	<section id="ChCapStopSection"><title>Stop the running capture</title>
    <para>
      A running capture session will be stopped in one of the following ways:
      <orderedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>Using the 
	  "<inlinegraphic entityref="WiresharkToolbarCaptureStop" format="PNG"/>
	  Stop" button from the <command>Capture Info dialog box
	  </command>.
	  </para>
	  <note><title>Note!</title>
	  <para>
	  The Capture Info dialog box might be hidden, if the option "Hide capture 
	  info dialog" is used.
	  </para>
	  </note>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>Using the <command>menu item</command>
	  "Capture/<inlinegraphic entityref="WiresharkToolbarCaptureStop" format="PNG"/>
	  Stop". 
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>Using the <command>toolbar item</command>
	  "<inlinegraphic entityref="WiresharkToolbarCaptureStop" format="PNG"/>
	  Stop". 
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>Pressing the accelerator keys: <command>Ctrl+E</command>. 
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>The capture will be automatically stopped, if one of the 
	  <command>Stop Conditions</command> is exceeded, e.g. the maximum amount 
	  of data was captured.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </para>
    </section>
	<section id="ChCapRestartSection"><title>Restart a running capture</title>
    <para>
      A running capture session can be restarted with the same capture options 
	  than the last time, this will remove all packets previously captured.
	  This can be useful, if some uninteresting packets are captured and 
	  there's no need to keep them.
    </para>
    <para>	  
	  Restart is a convenience function and 
	  equivalent to a capture stop following by an immediate capture start. 
	  A restart can be triggered in one of the following ways:
      <orderedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>Using the <command>menu item</command>
	  "Capture/<inlinegraphic entityref="WiresharkToolbarCaptureRestart" format="PNG"/>
	  Restart". 
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>Using the <command>toolbar item</command> 
	  "<inlinegraphic entityref="WiresharkToolbarCaptureRestart" format="PNG"/>
	  Restart". 
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </para>
    </section>
    </section>

</chapter>
<!-- End of WSUG Chapter Capture -->

